[
  {
    "unique_id": "190617",
    "question": "Angiotensinogen is converted into Angiotensin I by?",
    "answer": "Renin",
    "explanation": "A fall in glomerular blood flow/glomerular blood pressure/GFR can activate the JG cells to release renin which converts angiotensinogen in blood to angiotensin I and further to angiotensin II. Reference  :  NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 297",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Excretory Products and their Elimination >> Regulation of Kidney Function",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Aldosterone",
    "option_b": "Angiotensin II",
    "option_c": "ACE",
    "option_d": "Renin",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 1
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "290602",
    "question": "Hugo deVries was a scientist in the first decade of the _________ century.",
    "answer": "Twentieth",
    "explanation": "In the first decade of the twentieth century, Hugo deVries based on his work on evening primrose brought forth the idea of mutations – large differences arising suddenly in a population.",
    "topic_name": "Genetics and Evolution >> Evolution >> Mechanism of Evolution",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Twentieth",
    "option_b": "Nineteenth",
    "option_c": "Sixteenth",
    "option_d": "Eighteenth",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 2
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170336",
    "question": "All of the following are correct except:",
    "answer": "Vital Capacity (VC) is equal to sum of  ERV, TV and RV",
    "explanation": "Vital Capacity (VC): The maximum volume of air a person can breathe in after a forced expiration. This includes ERV, TV and IRV or the maximum volume of air a person can breathe out after a forced inspiration. (NCERT Class 11, Page 272)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Human Respiratory System",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Total Lung capacity is the highest parameter in spirometry",
    "option_b": "Vital Capacity (VC) is equal to sum of  ERV, TV and RV",
    "option_c": "Total Lung Capacity is equal to Vital capacity + residual volume.",
    "option_d": "Functional Residual Capacity (FRC) is equal to Volume of air that will remain in the lungs after a normal expiration.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 3
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250328",
    "question": "All the organs of female reproductive system are integrated structurally and functionally to support the processes of  \n\ni.Ovulation        \nii.Pregnancy,birth        \niii.fertilisation   \niv.Spermatogenesis",
    "answer": "i, ii and iii",
    "explanation": "All organs of female reproductive system are integrated structurally and functionally to support the processes of ovulation, fertilisation, pregnancy, birth and child Reference  : NCERT Page 47",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> The Female Reproductive System 1",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "ii and iv",
    "option_b": "i, ii and iii",
    "option_c": "i and iii",
    "option_d": "iii and iv",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 4
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170314",
    "question": "The fluid present between the layers of pleura ",
    "answer": "Pleural fluid",
    "explanation": "Pleural fluid is present between the layers of pleura. It reduces friction on the lung-surface. NCERT biology class 11, pg 269",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Human Respiratory System",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Coelomic fluid",
    "option_b": "Pleural fluid",
    "option_c": "Vesicular fluid",
    "option_d": "Circulatory fluid",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 5
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181841",
    "question": "Choose the correct option regarding the following assertion(A) and reason(R): \n\nA: Hypertension refers to elevated blood pressures. \n\nR: A person suffers from hypertension when his/her blood pressure becomes greater than 120/80 mm of H₂O.",
    "answer": "A is true but R is false",
    "explanation": "Hypertension occurs when blood pressure in a person becomes greater than 120/80 mm Hg (mercury not water). (NCERT Class 11 pg 287)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Assertion Reason and Multiple statement questions",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Both A and R are correct, and R is the correct explanation of A.",
    "option_b": "Both A and R are correct, and R is not the correct explanation of A.",
    "option_c": "A is true but R is false",
    "option_d": "Both A and R are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 6
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250703",
    "question": "Which of the following phase does Menstruation cycle starts with?",
    "answer": "Menstrual phase",
    "explanation": "Menstruation cycle starts with menstrual phase. Reference  : NCERT Page 49",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Menstrual Cycle",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Menstrual phase",
    "option_b": "Follicular phase",
    "option_c": "Luteal Phase",
    "option_d": "Ovulation phase",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 7
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170317",
    "question": "The exchange part of the respiratory system is formed by",
    "answer": "Alveoli and alveolar ducts",
    "explanation": "The alveoli and their ducts form the respiratory or exchange part of the respiratory system. NCERT biology class 11, pg 269",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Human Respiratory System",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Alveoli and alveolar ducts",
    "option_b": "Glottis and epiglottis",
    "option_c": "Bronchi and bronchioles",
    "option_d": "Nostrils and nasal passage",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 8
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "261216",
    "question": "Consider the statements regarding spreading information related to reproductive health. Choose the correct option.\n\n 1. Proper information about reproductive organs, adolescence and related changes, safe and hygienic sexual practices, sexually transmitted diseases (STD), AIDS, etc., would help people, especially those in the adolescent age group to lead a reproductively healthy life.\n\n 2. Educating people, especially fertile couples and those in the marriageable age group, about available birth control options, care of pregnant mothers, post-natal care of the mother and child, the importance of breastfeeding, equal opportunities for the male and the female child, etc., would address the importance of bringing up socially conscious healthy families of the desired size.\n\n 3. Introduction of sex education in schools should not be encouraged as it provides a lot more information than needed. \n\n 4. Awareness of problems due to uncontrolled population growth, social evils like sex abuse and sex-related crimes, etc., need to be created to enable people to think and take up necessary steps to prevent them and thereby build up a socially responsible and healthy society.",
    "answer": "only 3 is incorrect",
    "explanation": "The introduction of sex education in schools should also be encouraged to provide the right information to the young to discourage children from believing in myths and having misconceptions about sex-related aspects. Proper information about reproductive organs, adolescence and related changes, safe and hygienic sexual practices, sexually transmitted diseases (STD), AIDS, etc., would help people, especially those in the adolescent age group to lead a reproductively healthy life. Educating people, especially fertile couples and those in the marriageable age group, about available birth control options, care of pregnant mothers, post-natal care of the mother and child, the importance of breastfeeding, equal opportunities for the male and the female child, etc., would address the importance of bringing up socially conscious healthy families of the desired size. Awareness of problems due to uncontrolled population growth, social evils like sex abuse and sex-related crimes, etc., need to be created to enable people to think and take up necessary steps to prevent them and thereby build up a socially responsible and healthy society. (Reference   NCERT biology class 12; page no 58,  paragraph  no 2)",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Reproductive Health >> Assertion Reason and Multiple Statement Questions",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Both 1 and 2 are incorrect.",
    "option_b": "1,2 and 4 are incorrect. ",
    "option_c": "only 3 is incorrect",
    "option_d": "Both 2 and 3 are incorrect.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 9
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "230214",
    "question": "Bud formation takes place in.",
    "answer": "Yeast",
    "explanation": "In yeast, the division is unequal and small buds are produced that remain attached initially to the parent cell which, eventually gets separated and mature into new yeast organisms (cells).(Reference  :NCERT Biology Class 12: page no:6, paragraph no:1)",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Reproduction in Organisms >> Asexual Reproduction 1",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Paramecium",
    "option_b": "Amoeba",
    "option_c": "Yeast",
    "option_d": "Both Amoeba and Paramecium",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 10
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250310",
    "question": "Each fallopian tube is about________long",
    "answer": "10-12 cm",
    "explanation": "Each fallopian tube is about 10-12 cm long and extends from the periphery of each ovary to the uterus the part closer to the ovary is the funnel-shaped infundibulum. Reference  : NCERT Page 47",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> The Female Reproductive System 1",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "2- 4 mm",
    "option_b": "10- 12 mm",
    "option_c": "2- 4 cm",
    "option_d": "10-12 cm",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 11
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160551",
    "question": "Choose the correct statement \n\n(i)The final steps in digestion occurs far away from the mucosal epithelial cells of the intestine.\n\n(ii)The breakdown of biomacromolecules mentioned above occurs in the region before the jejunum of the small intestine.\n\n(iii)The simple substances thus formed are absorbed in the jejunum and ileum regions of the small intestine.\n\n(iv) The undigested and unabsorbed substances are stored in the large intestine and never excreted.",
    "answer": "Both (ii) and (iii)",
    "explanation": "The final steps in digestion occur very close to the mucosal epithelial cells of the intestine.\nDipeptides gets converted in to Amino acids through action of Dipeptidases. \nMaltose gets converted in to two molecules of Glucose through action of Maltase\nLactose gets converted in to Glucose + Galactose through action of Lactase\nSucrose gets converted in to Glucose+ Fructose through action of Sucrase                                     \nDi and Monoglycerides gets converted in to Fatty acids + Glycerol through action of  Lipases. \nThe breakdown of biomacromolecules mentioned above occurs in the duodenum (region preceding the jejunum)region of the small intestine. The simple substances thus formed are absorbed in the jejunum and ileum regions of the small intestine. The undigested and unabsorbed substances are passed on to the large intestine. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 263; Paragraph No. 5,6)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Digestion of food",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "(ii), (iii), (iv) ",
    "option_b": "Only (iv) ",
    "option_c": "Both (ii) and (iii)",
    "option_d": "(i), (ii), (iii), (iv)",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 12
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251109",
    "question": "Which of the following cells during gametogenesis is normally diploid? [AIPMT 2015 Cancelled]",
    "answer": "Spermatogonia",
    "explanation": "Spermatogonia are diploid germ cells of seminiferous tubules that undergo mitosis to form the primary spermatocytes. These primary spermatocytes are coverted to aploid sperms by meiotic of division. \n Reference  : NCERT Page 49",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Previous year questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Spermatogonia",
    "option_b": "Secondary polar body",
    "option_c": "Primary polar body",
    "option_d": "Spermatid",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 13
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160112",
    "question": "Who discovered organ of corti ?",
    "answer": "Alfonso corti",
    "explanation": "ALFONSO CORTI, the Italian anatomist, was born in 1822. Corti began his scientific career studying the cardiovascular systems of reptiles. Later, he turned his attention to the mammalian auditory system. In 1851, he published a paper describing a structure located on the basilar membrane of the cochlea containing hair cells that convert sound vibrations into nerve impulses, the organ of Corti. He died in the year 1888. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 257; Paragraph No.1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Introduction ",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Alfonso corti",
    "option_b": "Gregor Corti",
    "option_c": "Corti Catherine",
    "option_d": "Pavlov Corti",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 14
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181602",
    "question": "Splenic artery arises from [AIPMT 1991]",
    "answer": "Coeliac artery",
    "explanation": "The splenic artery is the blood vessel that supplies oxygenated blood to the spleen. It branches from the coeliac artery and follows a course superior to the pancreas. The coeliac artery is the first major branch of the abdominal aorta and branches from the aorta around the level of the T12 vertebra in humans. It is one of three anterior/ midline branches of the abdominal aorta. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 286; Paragraph No. 7)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Anterior mesenteric artery",
    "option_b": "Coeliac artery",
    "option_c": "Posterior mesenteric artery",
    "option_d": "Intestinal artery",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 15
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251202",
    "question": "Capacitation occurs in [NEET 2017]",
    "answer": "Female reproductive tract",
    "explanation": "The sperms in the female’s genital tract are made capable of fertilising the egg by secretions of the female genital tract. These secretions remove coating substances deposited on the surface of the sperms particularly those on the acrosome. Thus, the receptor sites on the acrosome are exposed and sperm becomes active to penetrate the egg. This phenomenon of sperm activation in mammals is known as capacitation. Reference  : NCERT Page 49",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Previous year questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Epididymis",
    "option_b": "Vas deferens",
    "option_c": "Female reproductive tract",
    "option_d": "Testis",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 16
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160328",
    "question": "The colon is divided into ______ parts",
    "answer": "4",
    "explanation": "The ileum opens into the large intestine. It consists of the caecum, colon and rectum. The caecum is a small blind sac which hosts some symbiotic micro-organisms. A narrow finger-like tubular projection, the vermiform appendix which is a vestigial organ, arises from the caecum. The caecum opens into the colon. The colon is divided into four parts – an ascending, a transverse, descending part and a sigmoid colon. The descending part opens into the rectum which opens out through the anus. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 259; Paragraph No. 1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Understanding the Alimentary Canal",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "1",
    "option_b": "2",
    "option_c": "3",
    "option_d": "4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 17
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250926",
    "question": "The first movements of the foetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during the ______ month.",
    "answer": "Fifth",
    "explanation": "The first movements of the foetus and appearance of hair on the head are usually observed during the fifth month.  Reference  : NCERT Page 54",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Pregnancy And Embryonic Development",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Second",
    "option_b": "Fifth",
    "option_c": "First",
    "option_d": "Nine",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 18
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250918",
    "question": "HCG, hPL and relaxin are produced in women only during",
    "answer": "Pregnancy",
    "explanation": "HCG, hPL and relaxin are produced in women only during pregnancy.  Reference  : NCERT Page 54",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Pregnancy And Embryonic Development",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Ovulation",
    "option_b": "Lactation",
    "option_c": "Puberty",
    "option_d": "Pregnancy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 19
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251118",
    "question": "Menstrual flow occurs due to lack of [AIPMT 2013]",
    "answer": "Progesterone",
    "explanation": "The corpus luteum secretes large amount of progesterone which is essential for maintenance of the endometrium necessary for implantation of the fertilized ovum and other events of pregnancy. In the absence of fertilization, the corpus luteum degenerates. This causes disintegration of the endometrium leading to menstruation. The menstrual flow results due to breakdown of endometrial lining of the uterus and its blood vessels which forms liquid that comes out through vagina. Reference  : NCERT Page 51",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Previous year questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Oxytocin",
    "option_b": "Vasopressin",
    "option_c": "Progesterone",
    "option_d": "FSH.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 20
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251204",
    "question": "In human females, meiosis-II is not completed until [AIPMT 2015]",
    "answer": "Fertilisation.",
    "explanation": "In human beings, ovum is released from the ovary in the secondary oocyte stage. The maturation of secondary oocyte is completed in the mother’s oviduct (fallopian tube) usually after the sperm has entered the secondary oocyte for fertilisation. Entry of the sperm restarts the cell cycle breaking down MPF (M-phase promoting factor) and turning on APC (Anaphase promoting complex). Completion of meiosis II converts the secondary oocyte into a fertilised ovum (egg) or zygote (and also a second polar body). Reference  : NCERT Page 52",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Previous year questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Uterine implantation",
    "option_b": "Birth",
    "option_c": "Puberty",
    "option_d": "Fertilisation.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 21
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181610",
    "question": "Child death may occur in the marriage of- [AIPMT 1988]",
    "answer": "RH⁺ man and Rh– woman",
    "explanation": "Rh factor plays a crucial role in child’s birth born out of a marriage between Rh– woman and a RH⁺ man. In such a case, the mother becomes sensitive while carrying a first RH⁺ child within her womb. The reason for such sensitivity is that some of the RBCs from the developing embryo get into the bloodstream of the mother during development, causing her to produce anti-Rh antibodies. In fact, the first child of such parents is nearly normal and is delivered safely. However, if such a mother gets pregnant again, the subsequent RH⁺ foetuses will be exposed to the anti-Rh antibodies produced by the mother. As a result serious damage to the red blood cells of the developing embryo will occur causing haemolytic disease of the newborn (HDN) or erythroblastosis fetalis. This disease leads to the death of the developing embryo before birth or after parturition. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 281; Paragraph No. 1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "RH⁺ man and RH⁺ woman",
    "option_b": "RH⁺ man and Rh– woman",
    "option_c": "Rh– man and Rh– woman",
    "option_d": "Rh– man and RH⁺ woman",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 22
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251404",
    "question": "Choose the correct statement/statements-:\n\n1. Testis have 500 compartments called as testicular lobules\n\n2. Male germ cells present inside the Seminiferous tubules are called as spermatids.\n\n3. Male germ cells undergo meiosis followed by mitosis finally.\n\n4. Leydig cells synthesize androgens.",
    "answer": "4 only ",
    "explanation": "The testis is covered by a dense covering. Each testis has about 250 compartments called testicular lobules\nEach seminiferous tubule is lined on its inside by two types of cells called male germ cells (spermatogonia) and Sertoli cells.\nThe male germ cells undergo meiotic divisions finally leading to sperm formation,\nLeydig cells synthesise and secrete testicular hormones called androgens.\n(Reference   NCERT BIO 12th , page no 43, 2nd paragraph )",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human reproduction >> Assertion Reason and Multiple statement questions",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": " 1and 4",
    "option_b": " 2 and 4",
    "option_c": "4 only ",
    "option_d": "2 only ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 23
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250619",
    "question": "For normal fertility, at least _______ sperms must have normal shape and size",
    "answer": "60%",
    "explanation": "The human male ejaculates about 200 to 300 million sperms during a coitus of which, for normal fertility, at least 60 % sperms must have normal shape and size.Reference  : NCERT Page 48",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Gametogenesis 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "40%",
    "option_b": "60%",
    "option_c": "80%",
    "option_d": "20%",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 24
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250602",
    "question": "FSH acts on the __________ and stimulates secretion of some factors which help in the process of spermiogenesis",
    "answer": "Sertoli cells",
    "explanation": "FSH acts on the Sertoli cells and stimulates secretion of some factors which help in the process of spermiogenesis. Reference  : NCERT Page 47",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Gametogenesis 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Vasa efferentia",
    "option_b": "Sertoli cells",
    "option_c": "Epididymis",
    "option_d": "Vas deferens",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 25
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181628",
    "question": "A vein possesses a large lumen because [AIPMT 1990]",
    "answer": "Tunica media is a thin coat",
    "explanation": "Wall of a vein consists of tunica externa, tunica media and tunica interna. All these layers are also present in the wall of artery. However, in the wall of a vein, the elastic membrane of tunica interna is relatively thin, and muscle fibres and elastic fibres in tunica media are fewer. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 286; Paragraph No. 6)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Tunica media and tunica externa form a single coat",
    "option_b": "Tunica interna and tunica media form a single coat",
    "option_c": "Tunica interna, tunica media and tunica externa are thin",
    "option_d": "Tunica media is a thin coat",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 26
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170613",
    "question": "Which of the following ion transports most of the CO₂",
    "answer": "HCO₃⁻",
    "explanation": "70 percent of CO₂ is carried as bicarbonate (HCO₃⁻) ion. NCERT biology class 11, pg 274",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Exchange of Gases and Transport of Gases",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "CO₃²⁻",
    "option_b": "HCO₃⁻",
    "option_c": "Cl⁻",
    "option_d": "H⁺",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 27
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181710",
    "question": "Anti-serum contains [AIIMS 1997]",
    "answer": "Antibodies",
    "explanation": "Anti-serum is a blood serum that contains antibodies. Serum is the fluid that separates from blood plasma on centrifugation. Serum is essentially similar in composition to plasma but lacks fibrinogen and other substances that are used in the coagulation process. But it contains the antigens and antibodies.  (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 279; Paragraph No. 1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year AIIMS Questions",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Antigens",
    "option_b": "Antibodies",
    "option_c": "Leucocytes",
    "option_d": "RBCs",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 28
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251217",
    "question": "Which part of mammary glands secrete Milk?",
    "answer": "Alveoli",
    "explanation": "Alveoli of the mammary gland secretes milk and it passes through the alveolar ducts, mammary ducts, lactiferous ducts and passes through the nipple",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Previous year questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Alveoli",
    "option_b": "Nipple",
    "option_c": "Lactiferous duct",
    "option_d": "Mammary duct",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 29
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250729",
    "question": "In human beings, menstrual cycles ceases around 50 years of age that is termed as",
    "answer": "Menopause",
    "explanation": "In human beings, menstrual cycles ceases around 50 years of age; that is termed as menopause. Reference  : NCERT Page 50",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Menstrual Cycle",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Menarche",
    "option_b": "Puberty",
    "option_c": "Menopause",
    "option_d": "Fertilisation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 30
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170417",
    "question": "How does the lateral thoracic wall move during inspiration?",
    "answer": "Outward and upward",
    "explanation": "The lateral thoracic wall moves outward and upward. NCERT biology class 11, pg 271",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Mechanism of Breathing",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Outward and upward",
    "option_b": "Inward and upward",
    "option_c": "Outward and downward",
    "option_d": "Inward and upward",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 31
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250813",
    "question": "Assertion: Not all copulations lead to fertilisation and pregnancy. \n\nReason: Fertilisation can only occur if the ovum and sperms are transported simultaneously to the ampullary region",
    "answer": "Both Assertion and Reason are true and Reason is the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "explanation": "Fertilisation can only occur if the ovum and sperms are transported simultaneously to the ampullary region. This is the reason why not all copulations lead to fertilisation and pregnancy. Reference   : NCERT Page 51",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Fertilisation and Implantation",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Both Assertion and Reason are true and Reason is the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "option_b": "Both Assertion and Reason are true but Reason is not the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but reason is fase",
    "option_d": "Both Assertion and Reason are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 32
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250917",
    "question": "Relaxin is secreted by ______  during ________ phase of pregnancy",
    "answer": "Ovary,late",
    "explanation": "Relaxin is mainly secreted by ovary during late phase of pregnancy from the corpus luteum. But however small amounts can be produced by the placenta,the question asks for the primary source , so the answer is ovary,more specifically the corpus luteum\nReference  : NCERT Page 53",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Pregnancy And Embryonic Development",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Placenta,late",
    "option_b": "Ovary,early",
    "option_c": "Ovary,late",
    "option_d": "Placenta,early",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 33
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170331",
    "question": "Choose the incorrect statement.",
    "answer": "Average residual volume is 2500mL to 3000 mL.",
    "explanation": "Residual Volume (RV) is Volume of air remaining in the lungs even after a forcible expiration. This averages 1100 mL to 1200 mL. (NCERT Class 11, Page (272)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Human Respiratory System",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "On an average, a healthy adult breathes 12-16 times/minute.",
    "option_b": "A spirometer is used to assess pulmonary functions.",
    "option_c": "A healthy man has a tidal volume of 500ml",
    "option_d": "Average residual volume is 2500mL to 3000 mL.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 34
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170339",
    "question": "Regarding respiration, Choose the incorrect pair.",
    "answer": "Tracheal Respiration---Humans",
    "explanation": "Explanation: Mechanisms of breathing vary among different groups of animals depending mainly on their habitats and levels of organisation.\n(NCERT Class 11, Page 268). Fishes respire through special vascularised structures called gills (branchial respiration)\nHumans and Reptiles respire through vascularised bags called lungs (pulmonary respiration).\nFrogs respire through lungs and also frogs can respire through their moist skin (cutaneous respiration)\n",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Human Respiratory System",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Branchial Respiration---fish",
    "option_b": "Tracheal Respiration---Humans",
    "option_c": "Pulmonary Respiration---Reptiles",
    "option_d": "Cutaneous Respiration---Frogs",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 35
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160111",
    "question": "Molecular physiology became almost synonymous with",
    "answer": "Biochemistry and biophysics",
    "explanation": "Molecular physiology became almost synonymous with biochemistry and biophysics. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 255; Paragraph No.1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Introduction ",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Biochemistry and biophysics",
    "option_b": "Astrology and physiology",
    "option_c": "Physiology and cytochemistry",
    "option_d": "Cytogenetics and molecular biology only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 36
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250640",
    "question": "Which of the following are mature Male Gametes?",
    "answer": "Spermatozoa",
    "explanation": "The spermatids are transformed into spermatozoa (sperms) by the process called spermiogenesis. Reference  : NCERT Page 47",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Gametogenesis 2",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Spermatid",
    "option_b": "Secondary spermatocytes",
    "option_c": "Spermatozoa",
    "option_d": "Primary spermatocyte",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 37
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181620",
    "question": "Difference between pulmonary artery and pulmonary vein is that, the pulmonary artery has [AIPMT 2000]",
    "answer": "Thicker walls",
    "explanation": "An artery has thick and more elastic wall but its lumen is narrow as compared to vein. Pulmonary artery carries deoxygenated blood from the right ventricle to the lungs for oxygenation. Pulmonary vein carries oxygenated blood from the lungs to the left auricle. Basically, each artery and vein consists of three layers: an inner lining of squamous endothelium, the tunica intima, a middle layer of smooth muscle and elastic fibres, the tunica media, and an external layer of fibrous connective tissue with collagen fibres, the tunica externa. The tunica media is comparatively thin in the veins. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 286; Paragraph No. 6)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "No endothelium",
    "option_b": "Valves",
    "option_c": "Thicker walls",
    "option_d": "Oxygenated blood",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 38
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181608",
    "question": "Which type of white blood cells are concerned with the release of histamine and the natural anticoagulant heparin? [AIPMT 2008]",
    "answer": "Basophils",
    "explanation": "Basophils have nucleus which is three-lobed and have less number of coarse granules. Their granules take basic stain and release heparin, histamine and serotonin. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 279; Paragraph No. 3)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Eosinophils",
    "option_b": "Monocytes",
    "option_c": "Neutrophils",
    "option_d": "Basophils",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 39
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181512",
    "question": "Component of blood responsible for producing antibodies is [AIPMT 1997]",
    "answer": "Lymphocytes",
    "explanation": "Lymphocytes have a very large, rounded nucleus and scanty cytoplasm. They are nonmotile and nonphagocytic. They secrete antibodies to destroy microbes and their toxins, reject grafts and kill tumour cells. They also help in healing of injuries. Thrombocytes aid in clotting of blood. Monocytes are phagocytic in nature and erythrocytes (RBCs) transport gases in the body. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 279; Paragraph No. 4)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Thrombocytes",
    "option_b": "Monocytes",
    "option_c": "Erythrocytes",
    "option_d": "Lymphocytes",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 40
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250816",
    "question": "The secretions of the acrosome help the sperm enter into the cytoplasm of the ovum through the __________",
    "answer": "Zona pellucida and plasma membrane",
    "explanation": "The secretions of the acrosome help the sperm enter into the cytoplasm of the ovum through the zona pellucida and plasma membrane. Reference   : NCERT Page 51",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Fertilisation and Implantation",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Zona pellucida only",
    "option_b": "Plasma membrane only",
    "option_c": "Zona pellucida and plasma membrane",
    "option_d": "Cell wall",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 41
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251402",
    "question": "Choose the correct statement/statements \n\n1. Testis are present outside the abdominal cavity but within the scrotum.\n\n2. Scrotum maintains the volume of testis at 2 to 2.5 mL higher than original volume for expansion during intercourse.\n\n3.Scrotum maintains the temperature of testis at 2 to 2.5 degree lower than the body.\n\n4. Testis have a globular shape.\n[NEET 2022]",
    "answer": "1 and 3 ",
    "explanation": "The testes are situated outside the abdominal cavity within a pouch called scrotum. \nThe scrotum helps in maintaining the low temperature of the testes (2–2.5 degrees C lower than the normal internal body temperature) necessary for spermatogenesis.They have no affect on the volume.\nIn adults, each testis is oval in shape,\n(Reference   NCERT BIO 12th , page no 43, 1st paragraph )",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human reproduction >> Assertion Reason and Multiple statement questions",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": " 1 only",
    "option_b": "2 and 4 ",
    "option_c": "1 and 2",
    "option_d": "1 and 3 ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 42
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160106",
    "question": "The food we eat is?",
    "answer": "More of Bio-Macromolecules",
    "explanation": "The major components of our food are carbohydrates, proteins and fats. all of these are biomacromolecules which need to be broken down via digestion. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 257; Paragraph No. 1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Introduction ",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "More of Bio-Macromolecules",
    "option_b": "More of Simple Substance",
    "option_c": "both simple substances and biomacromolecules in equal amount",
    "option_d": "Fats",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 43
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160609",
    "question": "Micelles are re-formed into very small protein coated fat globules called the  ",
    "answer": "Chylomicrons",
    "explanation": "Fatty acids and glycerol are first incorporated into small droplets called micelles which move into the intestinal mucosa. They are re-formed into very small protein-coated fat globules called the chylomicrons which are transported into the lymph vessels (lacteals) in the villi. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 265; Paragraph No. 1)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Absorption of Digested Producrs ",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Chylomicrons",
    "option_b": "Chyme",
    "option_c": "Bolus",
    "option_d": "Villi ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 44
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251442",
    "question": "ASSERTION-: Seminiferous tubules are coiled structures \n\nREASON-: They are lined by Sertoli cells",
    "answer": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is NOT the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "explanation": "The production of sperms in the testes takes place in a highly coiled structure called the seminiferous tubules.\nEach lobule contains one to three highly coiled seminiferous tubules in which sperms are produced. Each seminiferous tubule is lined on its inside by two types of cells called male germ cells (spermatogonia) and Sertoli cells.\n  (Reference   NCERT BIO 12th , page no 55, Summary)",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human reproduction >> Assertion Reason and Multiple statement questions",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_b": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is NOT the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but reason is false.",
    "option_d": "Assertion is false but reason is true.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 45
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "260711",
    "question": "Which of the following is one of the safest method of birth control?",
    "answer": "Sterilisation Techniques",
    "explanation": "Sterilisation Technique is the safest method of contraception as it prevents the occurance of any further pregnancies.",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Reproductive Health >> Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP)",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "The Rhythm Method",
    "option_b": "Sterilisation Techniques",
    "option_c": "Use of Physical Barriers",
    "option_d": "Termination of unwanted pregnancy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 46
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "380912",
    "question": "Who among the following was associated with Bishnoi movement?",
    "answer": "Amrita Devi",
    "explanation": "Amrita Devi sacrificed her life along with her three daughters in year 1730 during Bishnoi movement to save green trees being felled by the Maharaja of Jodhpur at a place known as Khejarli in Marwar, Rajasthan. Hence, A is the correct option.",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Environmental Issues >> Deforestation",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Amrita Devi",
    "option_b": "Sunder Lal Bahaguna",
    "option_c": "Govind Singh Rawat",
    "option_d": "Shamsher Singh Bisht",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 47
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250904",
    "question": "After birth, colostrum is released from mammary glands which is rich in",
    "answer": "Proteins, antibodies and low in fat",
    "explanation": "After birth, colostrum is released from mammary glands which is rich in Proteins, antibodies and low in fat. Reference  : NCERT Page 54",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Pregnancy And Embryonic Development",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Fat and low in proteins",
    "option_b": "Proteins and low in fat",
    "option_c": "Proteins, antibodies and low in fat",
    "option_d": "Proteins, fat and low in antibodies",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 48
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251431",
    "question": "Choose the correct statement/statements-:\n\n1. During the luteal phase corpus luteum changes to corpus albicans, when fertilzation takes place.\n\n2. Corpus luteum secretes estrogen, HCG, and progesterone which help in proliferation and maintenence of the endometrium \n\n3. Menstrual cycle ceases at around 40 years due to degeneration of ovaries\n\n4. Both LH and FSH attain a peak level in the middle of the cycle ",
    "answer": "4 only ",
    "explanation": "The ovulation (ovulatory phase) is followed by the luteal phase during which the remaining parts of the Graafian follicle transform as the corpus luteum. The corpus luteum secretes large amounts of progesterone which is essential for maintenance of the endometrium. Such an endometrium is necessary for implantation of the fertilised ovum and other events of pregnancy. During pregnancy all events of the menstrual cycle stop and there is no menstruation. In the absence of fertilisation, the corpus luteum degenerates. This causes disintegration of the endometrium leading to menstruation, marking a new cycle. In human beings, menstrual cycles ceases around 50 years of age; that is termed as menopause. \n\n- Both LH and FSH attain a peak level in the middle of cycle (about 14th day). Rapid secretion of LH leading to\nits maximum level during the mid-cycle called LH surge induces rupture of Graafian follicle and thereby the release of ovum (ovulation).\n(Reference   NCERT BIO 12th , page no 51,1st paragraph)",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human reproduction >> Assertion Reason and Multiple statement questions",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "1 and 4",
    "option_b": "2 and 3only ",
    "option_c": "4 only ",
    "option_d": "1,2 and 4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 49
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "380404",
    "question": "Irreparable computers and other electronic goods constitute",
    "answer": "Electronic waste",
    "explanation": "Irreparable computers and other electronic goods are known as electronic wastes (e-wastes).",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Environmental Issues >> Solid Wastes",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Hospital waste",
    "option_b": "Radioactive wastes",
    "option_c": "Electronic waste",
    "option_d": "Municipal solid wastes",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 50
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160710",
    "question": "True statements about marasmus\n\n(i)It is found in infants less than a year in age, if mother’s milk is replaced too early by other foods which are poor in both proteins and caloric value \n\n(ii)It is often happens if the mother has second pregnancy or childbirth when the older infant is still too old. \n\n(iii)Its occurs due to fats deficiency \n\n(iv)This often happens if the mother has second pregnancy or childbirth when the older infant is still too young.",
    "answer": "Both (i) and (iv) ",
    "explanation": "Marasmus is produced by a simultaneous deficiency of proteins and calories. It is found in infants less than a year in age if a mother’s milk is replaced too early by other foods which are poor in both proteins and caloric value. This often happens if the mother has second pregnancy or childbirth when the older infant is still too young. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 266; Paragraph No. 2)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Disorders of digestive system",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "(i), (ii), (iii), (iv)",
    "option_b": "(i), (ii), (iv)",
    "option_c": "(i), (iii), (iv)",
    "option_d": "Both (i) and (iv) ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 51
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250629",
    "question": "The theca layer is organised into:",
    "answer": "An inner theca interna and an outer theca externa",
    "explanation": "The theca are divided into two layers, the theca interna and the theca externa. Theca cells are a group of endocrine cells in the ovary made up of connective tissue surrounding the follicle.Reference  : NCERT Page 48",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Gametogenesis 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "An inner theca interna",
    "option_b": "An outer theca externa",
    "option_c": "An inner theca interna and an outer theca externa",
    "option_d": "An outer theca interna",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 52
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "251426",
    "question": "ASSERTION-: Zona pellucida is a covering that is around secondary oocyte\n\nREASON-: The sperm head is covered by acrosome which contains enzymes ",
    "answer": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is NOT the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "explanation": "The secondary oocyte forms a new membrane called zona pellucida surrounding it.\nDuring fertilisation, a sperm comes in contact with the zona pellucida layer of the ovum (Figure 3.10) and induces\nchanges in the membrane that block the entry of additional sperms. Thus, it ensures that only one sperm can fertilise an ovum.\nThe sperm head contains an elongated haploid nucleus, the anterior portion of which is covered by a cap-like structure, acrosome. The acrosome is filled with enzymes that help fertilisation of the ovum. The sperm head contains an elongated haploid nucleus, the anterior portion of which is covered by a cap-like structure, acrosome. The acrosome is filled with enzymes that help fertilisation of the ovum. (Reference   NCERT BIO 12th , page no 49, 1st paragraph )",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human reproduction >> Assertion Reason and Multiple statement questions",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_b": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is NOT the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_c": " Assertion is true but reason is false.",
    "option_d": "Assertion is false but reason is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 53
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160545",
    "question": "How many of given enzymes are present in pancreatic juice.      \nsalivary amylase, Lysozyme , pepsinogen,  pepsin, Rennin, lipases, trypsinogen, chymotrypsinogen, enterokinase, procarboxypeptidases, amylases, nucleases. ",
    "answer": "6",
    "explanation": "The pancreatic juice contains inactive enzymes – trypsinogen, chymotrypsinogen, procarboxypeptidases, amylases, lipases and nucleases. Trypsinogen is activated by an enzyme, enterokinase, secreted by the intestinal mucosa into active trypsin, which in turn activates the other enzymes in the pancreatic juice. ",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Digestion of food",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "6",
    "option_b": "4",
    "option_c": "5",
    "option_d": "7",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 54
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "150906",
    "question": "The active substances in the bakanae disease was later on found to be?",
    "answer": "Gibberellic acid",
    "explanation": "The ‘bakanae’ (foolish seedling) disease of rice seedlings, was caused by a fungal pathogen Gibberella fujikuroi. E. Kurosawa (1926) reported the appearance of symptoms of the disease in rice seedlings when the were treated with sterile infiltrates of the fungus. The active substances were later identified as gibberellic acid.",
    "topic_name": "Plant Physiology >> Plant Growth and Development >> The Discovery of Plant Growth Regulators",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Auxin",
    "option_b": "Ethylene",
    "option_c": "Cytokinin",
    "option_d": "Gibberellic acid",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 55
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "21211",
    "question": "Assertion: Fungi are cosmopolitan and occur in air, water, soil and on animals and plants.\n\n\nReason: They prefer to grow in warm and humid places.",
    "answer": "Both Assertion and Reason are true but Reason is not the correct explanation of Assertion.",
    "explanation": "Fungi are cosmopolitan and occur in air, water, soil and on animals and plants. They prefer to grow in warm and humid places. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 22; Paragraph No. 5)",
    "topic_name": "Diversity In Living World >> Biological Classification >> Assertion and Reason and Multiple Statement Questions Part 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Both Assertion and Reason are true and Reason is the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "option_b": "Both Assertion and Reason are true but Reason is not the correct explanation of Assertion.",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but Reason is false.",
    "option_d": "Both Assertion and Reason are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 56
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "361034",
    "question": "With regards to Ecological pyramids, Which of the following statements is incorrect ? ",
    "answer": "Ecological pyramids can accomodate a simple food web",
    "explanation": "However, there are certain limitations of ecological pyramids such as it does not take into account the same species belonging to two or more trophic levels. It assumes a simple food chain, something that almost never exists in nature; it does not accommodate a food web. Moreover, saprophytes are not given any place in ecological pyramids even though they play a vital role in the ecosystem.\nReference: NCERT class 12, chapter 14, page 250",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >>  Assertion Reason and Mutliple statement questions Part 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Ecological pyramids such as it does not take into account the same species belonging to two or more trophic levels",
    "option_b": "Ecological pyramids assume a simple food chain, something that almost never exists in nature;",
    "option_c": "Ecological pyramids can accomodate a simple food web",
    "option_d": "Saprophytes are not given any place in ecological pyramids even though they play a vital role in the ecosystem.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 57
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "170207",
    "question": "Which of the following amphibians undergo cutaneous respiration",
    "answer": "Frogs",
    "explanation": "Amphibians like frogs can respire through their moist skin called cutaneous respiration. NCERT biology class 11, pg ",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Respiratory Organs",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Icthyus",
    "option_b": "Frogs",
    "option_c": "Snakes",
    "option_d": "Newts",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 58
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "361103",
    "question": "With regards to the Carbon Cycle,Choose the incorrect statement",
    "answer": "Deforestation causes depletion of CO₂  from the atmosphere and afforestation increases the CO₂  content in the atmosphere.",
    "explanation": "Some amount of the fixed carbon is lost to sediments and removed from circulation. Burning of wood, forest fire and combustion of organic matter, fossil fuel, volcanic activity are additional sources for releasing CO₂  in the atmosphere. Human activities have significantly influenced the carbon cycle. Rapid deforestation and massive burning of fossil fuel for energy and transport have significantly increased the rate of release of  CO₂  into the atmosphere (see greenhouse effect in Chapter 16).\nAfforestation is planting of trees, and they do not increase  CO₂  levels, they inturn cause fall in CO₂  levels as they get fixed by photosynthesis.\n\nReference: NCERT class 12, chapter 14, page 254",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >>  Assertion Reason and Mutliple statement questions Part 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Some amount of the fixed carbon is lost to sediments and removed from circulation. ",
    "option_b": "Burning of wood, forest fire and combustion of organic matter, fossil fuel, volcanic activity are additional sources for releasing CO₂  in the atmosphere",
    "option_c": "Rapid deforestation and massive burning of fossil fuel for energy and transport have significantly increased the rate of release of  CO₂  into the atmosphere.",
    "option_d": "Deforestation causes depletion of CO₂  from the atmosphere and afforestation increases the CO₂  content in the atmosphere.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 59
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "310502",
    "question": "Which of the following food item has high nutritive value and also finds use in the indigenous systems of medicine.",
    "answer": "Honey",
    "explanation": "Honey is a food of high nutritive value and also finds use in the indigenous systems of medicine.",
    "topic_name": "Biology In Human Welfare >> Strategies for enhancement in food production >> Bee keeping",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Honey",
    "option_b": "Banana",
    "option_c": "Apricot",
    "option_d": "Chickpeas",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 60
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "360915",
    "question": "Which one of the following is not a function of an ecosystem? [2013]",
    "answer": "Stratification",
    "explanation": "Four important functional aspects of the ecosystem are \n(i) productivity \n\n(ii) decomposition, \n\n(iii) energy flow and \n\n(iv) nutrient cycling.",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Energy flow",
    "option_b": "Decomposition",
    "option_c": "Productivity",
    "option_d": "Stratification",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 61
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "360741",
    "question": "In the ecosystem services, the soil formation accounts for about ___ %",
    "answer": "50",
    "explanation": "In the ecosystem services, the soil formation accounts for about 50 %",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >> Nutrient Cycle and Ecosystem Services",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "50",
    "option_b": "60",
    "option_c": "40",
    "option_d": "30",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 62
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "290721",
    "question": "Natural selection leads to all except ________.",
    "answer": "Constant gene",
    "explanation": "Natural selection can lead to stabilization (in which more individuals acquire mean character value), directional change (more individuals acquire value other than the mean character value), or disruption (more individuals acquire peripheral character value at both ends of the distribution curve).",
    "topic_name": "Genetics and Evolution >> Evolution >> Hardy-Weinberg Principle",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Disruption",
    "option_b": "Stabilization",
    "option_c": "Directional change",
    "option_d": "Constant gene",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 63
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "310201",
    "question": "___________is the management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption.",
    "answer": "Dairying",
    "explanation": "Dairying is the management of animals for milk and its products for human consumption.",
    "topic_name": "Biology In Human Welfare >> Strategies for enhancement in food production >> Dairy Farm Management",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Animal husbandry",
    "option_b": "Livestock farming",
    "option_c": "Dairying",
    "option_d": "Poultry farming",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 64
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "151510",
    "question": "Which one of the following is not an example of biennial?",
    "answer": "Cucumbers",
    "explanation": "Sugarbeet, cabbages, carrots are some of the common biennials.",
    "topic_name": "Plant Physiology >> Plant Growth and Development >> Photoperiodism",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Cabbages",
    "option_b": "Carrots",
    "option_c": "Cucumbers",
    "option_d": "Sugarbeet",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 65
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "310104",
    "question": "Fisheries include rearing, catching, selling, etc., of ____________",
    "answer": "Crustaceans and Pisces",
    "explanation": "Fisheries include rearing, catching, selling, etc., of fish, molluscs (shell-fish) and crustaceans (prawns, crabs, etc.)Pisces represents Class of fish, while Crustaceans is a class that includes prawns, crabs and shrimps",
    "topic_name": "Biology In Human Welfare >> Strategies for enhancement in food production >> Animal Husbandry",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Crustaceans and Pisces",
    "option_b": "Algae and Arachnids",
    "option_c": "Pheretima and Prawns",
    "option_d": "Periplaneta and Pisces",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 66
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181511",
    "question": "Vitamin K is required for [AIPMT 1997]",
    "answer": "Vitamin K is essential for blood clotting as it is necessary for the synthesis of prothrombin in the liver.",
    "explanation": "Vitamin K is essential for blood clotting as it is necessary for the synthesis of prothrombin in the liver. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 281; Paragraph No. 2)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Body Fluids and circulation >> Previous Year Questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Change of prothrombin into thrombin",
    "option_b": "Vitamin K is essential for blood clotting as it is necessary for the synthesis of prothrombin in the liver.",
    "option_c": "Change of fibrinogen to fibrin",
    "option_d": "Formation of thromboplastin",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 67
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "361028",
    "question": "With regards to Ecological pyramids, which of the following statements is true",
    "answer": "Only three top-carnivores are supported in an ecosystem based on production of nearly 6 millions plants in a grassland ecosystem",
    "explanation": " The base of a pyramid is broad and it narrows towards the apex. One gets a similar shape, whether you express the food or energy relationship between organisms at different trophic levels. This, relationship is expressed in terms of number, biomass or energy. The base of each pyramid represents the producers or the first trophic level while the apex represents tertiary or top level consumer.Pyramid of biomass shows a sharp decrease in biomass at higher trophic levels, only three top-carnivores are supported in an ecosystem based on production of nearly 6 millions plants in a grassland ecosystem.Inverted pyramid of biomass-small standing crop of phytoplankton supports large standing crop of zooplankton. Any calculations of energy content, biomass or numbers, has to include all organisms at that trophic level, \nReference:  NCERT class 12, chapter 14, page 247 and 248 and refer to all images in page 248",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >>  Assertion Reason and Mutliple statement questions Part 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Only three top-carnivores are supported in an ecosystem based on production of nearly 6 millions plants in a grassland ecosystem",
    "option_b": "Pyramid of biomass shows a sharp increase in biomass at higher trophic levels",
    "option_c": "Erect pyramid of biomass is obtained when small standing crop of phytoplankton supports large standing crop of zooplankton",
    "option_d": "Any calculations of energy content, biomass or numbers, has to include only the top predators at that trophic level.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 68
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "151001",
    "question": "The word auxin is derived from Greek word 'auxein' which means",
    "answer": "To grow",
    "explanation": "Auxins (from Greek ‘auxein’ : to grow) was first isolated from human urine.",
    "topic_name": "Plant Physiology >> Plant Growth and Development >> Auxins",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "To differentiatie",
    "option_b": "To develop",
    "option_c": "To grow",
    "option_d": "To agitate",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 69
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "171113",
    "question": "In lungs, the air is separated from the venous blood through",
    "answer": "Squamous epithelium + endothelium of blood vessel",
    "explanation": "In lungs, the air is separated from the venous blood through squamous epithelium and endothelium of blood vessel. As a result, the barriers between the air in an alveolus and the blood in its capillaries is only about 0.5 mm",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Breathing and Exchange of Gases >> Previous Year Questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Transitional epithelium + tunica externa of blood vessel",
    "option_b": "Squamous epithelium + endothelium of blood vessel",
    "option_c": "Squamous epithelium + tunica media of blood vessel",
    "option_d": "Transitional epithelium + tunica media of blood vessel",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 70
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160530",
    "question": "Hormonal control of the secretion of digestive juices is carried out by local hormones produced by the \n(i)Gastric mucosa \n(ii)Intestinal mucosa \n(iii)Submucosal \n(iv) serosa",
    "answer": "Both (i) and (ii)",
    "explanation": "Hormonal control of the secretion of digestive juices is carried out by local hormones produced by the gastric and intestinal mucosa. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 264; Paragraph No. 3)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Digestion of food",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Both (i) and (ii)",
    "option_b": "Both (i) and (iii)",
    "option_c": "Both (ii) and (iii)",
    "option_d": "Both (iii) and (iv)",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 71
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "310506",
    "question": "Which of the following cant be pollinated by honeybees",
    "answer": "Banana",
    "explanation": "Bees are the pollinators of many of our crop species such as sunflower, Brassica, apple and pear",
    "topic_name": "Biology In Human Welfare >> Strategies for enhancement in food production >> Bee keeping",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Brassica",
    "option_b": "Pear",
    "option_c": "Banana",
    "option_d": "Sunflower",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 72
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "290603",
    "question": "Hugo deVries based on his work on ___________.",
    "answer": "Evening primrose",
    "explanation": "In the first decade of the twentieth century, Hugo deVries based on his work on evening primrose brought forth the idea of mutations – large differences arising suddenly in a population.",
    "topic_name": "Genetics and Evolution >> Evolution >> Mechanism of Evolution",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Chinese primrose",
    "option_b": "Primula veris",
    "option_c": "Evening primrose",
    "option_d": "Polyanthus",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 73
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "260713",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is not true?",
    "answer": "MTPs were legalised in India, in the year 1981",
    "explanation": "MTP plays an important role in decreasing the population. Government of India legalized MTPi in 1971, with certain restrictions to avoid its misuse. MTP is safe during the first trimester.",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Reproductive Health >> Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP)",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "MTP plays an important role in decreasing the population.",
    "option_b": "The Government of India legalized MTP with certain restrictions to avoid its misuse.",
    "option_c": "MTP is safe during the first trimester.",
    "option_d": "MTPs were legalised in India, in the year 1981",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 74
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "360805",
    "question": "In relation to Gross primary productivity and Net primary productivity of an ecosystem, which one of the following statements is correct? [NEET 2020]",
    "answer": "Gross primary productivity is always more than Net primary productivity.",
    "explanation": "Gross primary productivity (gpp) is the rate of production of organic matter during photosynthesis. A considerable amount of gpp is utilised by plants in respiration. Gpp minus respiration losses (r) is the net primary productivity gpp – r = npp. Therefore, gpp is always more than npp.",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >> Previous Year Questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Gross primary productivity is always less than Net primary productivity.",
    "option_b": "Gross primary productivity is always more than Net primary productivity.",
    "option_c": "Gross primary productivity and Net primary productivity are one and same.",
    "option_d": "There is no relationship between Gross primary productivity and Net primary productivity.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 75
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "90110",
    "question": "Analysis of compounds gives: ",
    "answer": "The organic and inorganic constituent present in living tissues",
    "explanation": "analysis for compounds gives an idea of the kind of organic and inorganic constituents present in living tissues.(Reference  :NCERT Biology Class 11; page no:143, paragraph no:1)",
    "topic_name": "Cell Structure And Functions >> Biomolecules >> Chemical Composition",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Organic constituent present in living tissues",
    "option_b": "The organic and inorganic constituent present in living tissues",
    "option_c": "Inorganic constituent present in living tissues",
    "option_d": "Elemental and compound composition",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 76
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "361008",
    "question": "Assertion: Primary Productivity varies with different ecosystems\n\nReason: Primary productivity is independent of plant species inhabiting a particular area,environmental factors, availability of nutrients and photosynthetic capacity of plants.",
    "answer": "Assertion is true, but reason is false",
    "explanation": "Primary productivity depends on the plant species inhabiting a particular area. It also depends on a variety of environmental factors, availability of nutrients and photosynthetic capacity of plants. Therefore, it varies in different types of ecosystems.Reference   NCERT class 12 biology chapter 14 page 243",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >>  Assertion Reason and Mutliple statement questions Part 1",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Both Assertion and Reason are true and Reason is the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "option_b": "Both Assertion and Reason are true and Reason is not the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true, but reason is false",
    "option_d": "Both Assertion and Reason are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 77
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "290709",
    "question": "The gene pool remains a constant. This is called _________.",
    "answer": "Genetic equilibrium",
    "explanation": "The gene pool (total genes and their alleles in a population) remains constant. This is called genetic equilibrium.",
    "topic_name": "Genetics and Evolution >> Evolution >> Hardy-Weinberg Principle",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Genetic reproduction",
    "option_b": "Genetic imbalance",
    "option_c": "Gene design",
    "option_d": "Genetic equilibrium",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 78
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "160522",
    "question": "The secretions of the brush border cells of the mucosa along with the secretions of the goblet cells constitute \n(i)Intestinal juice \n(ii)Succus entericus \n(iii)Pancreatic juice  \n(iv)Bile juice",
    "answer": "Both (i) and (ii)",
    "explanation": "The secretions of the brush border cells of the mucosa along with the secretions of the goblet cells constitute the intestinal juice or succus entericus. (Reference  : NCERT Biology Class 11; Page 262; Paragraph No. 5)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Digestion  and  Absorption >> Digestion of food",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Both (i) and (ii)",
    "option_b": "Both (i) and (iii)",
    "option_c": "Both (ii) and (iii)",
    "option_d": "Both (iii) and (iv)",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 79
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250110",
    "question": "Each seminiferous tubule is lined on its inside by______types of cells.",
    "answer": "Two",
    "explanation": "Each seminiferous tubule is lined on its inside by two types of cells called male germ cells (spermatogonia) and Sertoli cells\n(Reference  : NCERT PAGE 43)",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> The Male Reproductive System 1",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "One",
    "option_b": "Two",
    "option_c": "Three",
    "option_d": "Four",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 80
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250601",
    "question": "Spermatids are produced as a result of:",
    "answer": "Second meiotic division",
    "explanation": "The secondary spermatocytes undergo the second meiotic division to produce four equal, haploid spermatids. Reference  : NCERT Page 47",
    "topic_name": "Reproduction >> Human Reproduction >> Gametogenesis 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "First meiotic division",
    "option_b": "Mitosis",
    "option_c": "Second meiotic division",
    "option_d": "Third meiotic division",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 81
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "290710",
    "question": "How many factors are known to affect Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium? ",
    "answer": "Five",
    "explanation": "Five factors are known to affect the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. ",
    "topic_name": "Genetics and Evolution >> Evolution >> Hardy-Weinberg Principle",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "One",
    "option_b": "Three",
    "option_c": "Five",
    "option_d": "Seven",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 82
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "380606",
    "question": "Without greenhouse effect the average temperature at surface of Earth would have been _________",
    "answer": "-18 °C",
    "explanation": "Without greenhouse effect the average temperature at surface of Earth would have been a chilly –18 °C",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Environmental Issues >> Radioactive Wastes, Greenhouse effect and Global Warming",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "-2 °C",
    "option_b": "-9 °C",
    "option_c": "-18 °C",
    "option_d": "18 °C",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 83
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "151311",
    "question": "Ethylene is used to initiate flowering and for synchronising fruit-set in _______",
    "answer": "Pineapples",
    "explanation": "Ethylene is used to initiate flowering and for synchronising fruit-set in pineapples",
    "topic_name": "Plant Physiology >> Plant Growth and Development >> Ethylene",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Pineapples",
    "option_b": "Aloe vera",
    "option_c": "Eucalyptus",
    "option_d": "Rose plants",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 84
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "370903",
    "question": "Which of the following is the most important for animals and plants being driven to extinction? [NEET 2019]",
    "answer": "Habitat loss and fragmentation",
    "explanation": "Habitat loss and fragmentation is the most important cause of driving the animals and plants to extinction. When large habitats are broken into small fragments due to various human activities, mammals and birds requiring large territories and certain animals with migratory habitats are badly affected, leading to population declines. The same can be applicable to the plant (forest) loss and degradation as millions of species are being cut and cleared for the expansion of agricultural land, harvesting timber, forest fire, as well as overgrazing.\nReference  :NCERT Biology Class 12: Page No:264,paragraph no:5",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Biodiversity and Conservation >> Previous Year Questions 1",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Alien species invasion",
    "option_b": "Habitat loss and fragmentation",
    "option_c": "Drought and floods",
    "option_d": "Economic exploitation",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 85
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "211508",
    "question": "Which part of the brain is responsible for thermoregulation? [NEET 2019]",
    "answer": "Hypothalamus",
    "explanation": "Hypothalamus is thermoregulatory centre. Hence it is called “thermostat” of the body. It keeps body temperature at roughly 37°c by means of a complex thermostat system..(Reference  : NCERT biology class 11; page 321;paragraph no.1).",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Neural Control and Coordination >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Medulla oblongata",
    "option_b": "Cerebrum",
    "option_c": "Hypothalamus",
    "option_d": "Corpus callosum",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 86
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "360901",
    "question": "What type of ecological pyramid would be obtained with the following data? [NEET 2018]\n\nSecondary consumer : 120 g; \n\nPrimary consumer : 60 g; \n\nPrimary producer : 10 g ",
    "answer": "Inverted pyramid of biomass",
    "explanation": "The given data depicts the inverted pyramid of biomass, usually found in aquatic ecosystem. This can be understood by taking an example of a pond in which phytoplankton (10g) represents the producer. Small fishes (60g) feeding upon these phytoplankton represent primary consumers which are further eaten by the big fishes (120g) representing secondary consumers.",
    "topic_name": "Ecology >> Ecosystem >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Inverted pyramid of biomass",
    "option_b": "Pyramid of energy",
    "option_c": "Upright pyramid of numbers",
    "option_d": "Upright pyramid of biomass",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 87
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "211308",
    "question": "Sound vibrations are transmitted through the __________ to the oval window.",
    "answer": "ear ossicles",
    "explanation": "The eardrum vibrates in response to the sound waves and these vibrations are transmitted through the ear ossicles (malleus, incus and stapes) to the oval window. However the bone that directly connects to the oval window is Stapes.(Reference  : NCERT biology class 11; page 327;paragraph no.2)",
    "topic_name": "Human Physiology >> Neural Control and Coordination >> The Ear 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Malleus only",
    "option_b": "Incus only",
    "option_c": "ear ossicles",
    "option_d": "Tarsal",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 88
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "291102",
    "question": "Variations caused by mutation, as proposed by Hugo de Vries, are [NEET 2019]",
    "answer": "Random and directionless",
    "explanation": "Hugo de Vries (1901) put forward the theory of evolution called mutation theory. He believed that mutation causes evolution. Mutations are discontinuous variations that are random and directionless.",
    "topic_name": "Genetics and Evolution >> Evolution >> Previous Year Questions 2",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "Small and directionless",
    "option_b": "Random and directional",
    "option_c": "Random and directionless",
    "option_d": "Small and directional",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 89
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "21408",
    "question": "Consider the following Assertion and Reason and choose the correct option.\nAssertion- In sac fungi, mycelium is unbranched and septate. \n\n\nReason- The asexual spores are conidiophores produced exogenously on the special mycelium conidia. ",
    "answer": "Both Assertion and Reason are false",
    "explanation": "Mycelium is branched and septate. The asexual spores are conidia produced exogenously on the special mycelium called conidiophores. ",
    "topic_name": "Diversity In Living World >> Biological Classification >> Assertion and Reason and Multiple Statement Questions Part 3",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "Both Assertion and Reason are true and Reason is the correct explanation of Assertion",
    "option_b": "Both Assertion and Reason are true but Reason is not the correct explanation of Assertion.",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but Reason is false",
    "option_d": "Both Assertion and Reason are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 90
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "940118",
    "question": "Is it meaningful to add a component of a vector to the same vector?",
    "answer": "Meaningful",
    "explanation": "Adding a component of a vector to the same vector is meaningful as this represents the same  case of adding vectors with the same dimensions. In this, the magnitude of the resultant vector  will increase and the direction will remain the same. ",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 NCERT Book Back >> Motion in a Plane >> Set 1",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Meaningful",
    "option_b": "Not Meaningful",
    "option_c": "Some times meaningful other no",
    "option_d": "Not enough information to decide",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 91
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "820204",
    "question": "The current drawn by the primary of a transformer, which steps down 200 V to 20 V to operate a device of resistance 20Ω is (Assume the efficiency of the transformer to be 80%)?",
    "answer": "0.125 A",
    "explanation": "The formula for the efficiency of a transformer is given by:𝞰= P₀/Pᵢ=𝜺ₛIₛ/𝜺ₚIₚ Given: 𝜺ₚ= 200 V, R = 20Ω, 𝜺ₛ = 20 V, η = 80% Iₚ =? \nwe calculate secondary coils current, Iₛ = Vₛ/R = 20 V/20Ω = 1 A \nη = 𝜺ₛIₛ/𝜺ₚIₚ \nIₚ = 𝜺ₛIₛ /𝜺ₚη \nIₚ = (20×1×100)/(200×80) \nIₚ = 0.125 A",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Alternating Current >> Efficiency of  Transformers",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "0.125 A",
    "option_b": "0.225 A",
    "option_c": "0.325 A",
    "option_d": "0.425 A",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 92
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "490123",
    "question": "Coulomb is the unit of",
    "answer": "electric charge",
    "explanation": "Coulomb is the unit of electric charge.",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Set 8",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "electric charge",
    "option_b": "magnetic field",
    "option_c": "electric flux",
    "option_d": "magnetic flux",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 93
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "580127",
    "question": "The life span of atomic hydrogen is",
    "answer": "fraction of one second",
    "explanation": "fraction of one second \nvideo(_yw1ZWhXw_g)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Atoms >> Set 9",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "fraction of one second",
    "option_b": "one year",
    "option_c": "one hour",
    "option_d": "one day",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 94
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "540130",
    "question": "A microscope is focused on a mark on a piece of paper and then a slab of glass of thickness 6 cm and refractive index 1.5 is placed over the mark. How should the microscope be moved to get the mark in focus again?",
    "answer": "2 cm upward",
    "explanation": "Apparent depth = real depth /μ =6/1.5= 4 cm.\nAs image appears to be raised by 2 cm, therefore,\nMicroscope must be moved upwards by 2 cm        ",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics and Optical instrument >> Set 8",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "2 cm upward",
    "option_b": "1 cm upward",
    "option_c": "4.5 cm downward",
    "option_d": "1 cm downward",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 95
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450277",
    "question": "Two sources of sound placed close to each other, are emitting progressive waves given by y₁ = 6 sin 200 π t  and y₂  = 10 sin 256 π t. How many beats are produced per minute ?\n",
    "answer": "1680",
    "explanation": "Step 1:  y₁ = 6 sin 200 π t\n∴ ω₁ = 200 π \n2 π v₁ = 200 π \nv₁ = 100 Hz\n\nStep 2: y₂  = 10 sin 256 π t\n∴ ω₂ = 256 π\n2 π v₂ = 256 π \nv₂ = 128 Hz\n\nStep 3: Number of beats produced per minute = v₂ - v₁\n            = 128 - 100 \n            = 28 Hz \n            = 28 × 60 = 1680 \n",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 59",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "128",
    "option_b": "100",
    "option_c": "1580",
    "option_d": "1680",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 96
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450130",
    "question": "The equation of a progressive wave is y = 0.02 sin 2π ( 4t − 2.24 x ). Its wavelength  is",
    "answer": "0.446 unit",
    "explanation": "Step 1: y = 0.02 sin 2π ( 4t − 2.24 x )\n\nStep 2: k = 2π / λ\n\nStep 3: k = 2.24 × 2π\n\nStep 4: λ = 2π / k  \nλ = 2π / 2.24 × 2π\nλ = 0.446 unit\n",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 10",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "2.346 unit",
    "option_b": "0.446 unit",
    "option_c": "1.446 unit",
    "option_d": "0.346 unit",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 97
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450300",
    "question": "Consider two pianos A and B. Piano A has two strings with a frequency of 60 Hz and 40 Hz. And piano B has two strings with a frequency of 180 Hz  and 160 Hz. Number of beats produced in both piano are",
    "answer": "20",
    "explanation": "Step 1: Number of beats in piano A \nn  = v₁ - v₂ = 60 - 40 = 20 \n\nStep 2: Number of beats in piano B \nn =  v₁ - v₂ = 180 - 160 = 20 \n\nBoth piano has same number of beats = 20\n",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 67",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "10",
    "option_b": "20",
    "option_c": "60",
    "option_d": "40",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 98
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450243",
    "question": "A string fixed at its both ends vibrates in 2 loops as shown in the diagram\nThe total number of nodes and antinodes are respectively: diagram(n4501)",
    "answer": "3 , 2",
    "explanation": "From the figure\nTotal nodes = 3\nTotal antinodes = 2\ndiagram(ne4505)",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 48",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "3 , 2",
    "option_b": "2 , 3",
    "option_c": "3 , 4",
    "option_d": "4 , 3",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 99
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222401",
    "question": "What is the formula of power of a lens?",
    "answer": "p=1/f",
    "explanation": "The formula of power of lenses is :\np=1/f, where f is the focal length (Lecture 6; 07:51)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Power of lens",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "p=1/f",
    "option_b": "p=2/f",
    "option_c": "p=2f",
    "option_d": "p=f",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 100
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "221804",
    "question": "If the i > ic then what will happen?",
    "answer": "reflection",
    "explanation": "If i > ic, where ic is the critical angle of incidence, then the incident ray of light will undergo total internal reflection instead of refraction. This happens when light travels from a denser medium to a less dense medium, and the angle of incidence is greater than the critical angle. In this case, the refracted ray of light is not formed and all the light is reflected back into the denser medium. This phenomenon is commonly observed in optical fibers, mirages, and diamond cutting. (Lecture 3; 03:55)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Total internal reflection",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "reflection",
    "option_b": "refraction",
    "option_c": "absorption",
    "option_d": "all of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 101
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181702",
    "question": "What is the force experienced per unit length of the two conductors?",
    "answer": "μ₀I₁I₂/2πr",
    "explanation": "If I₁ is the current passing through first conductor, I₂ is the current passing through second conductor and 'r' is the distance between them. Then the magnitude of the magnetic force per unit length experienced by either of the conductors is: μ₀I₁I₂/2πr (Lecture 4; 08:36)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Force between two conductor that are parallel",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "μ₀I₁I₂/2πr",
    "option_b": "μ₀I₁I₂/2r",
    "option_c": "μ₀I₁I₂/r",
    "option_d": "μ₀I₁I₂/5π",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 102
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181708",
    "question": "The currents in the opposite direction imply which force?",
    "answer": "repulsive force",
    "explanation": "The currents in the opposite direction are equal to what force repulsive force. (Lecture 4; 12:30)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Force between two conductor that are parallel",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "repulsive force",
    "option_b": "attractive force",
    "option_c": "both a & b",
    "option_d": "none of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 103
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "151005",
    "question": "Which of the following is not an equation of travelling wave ",
    "answer": "y=Asin(wt-2𝞹λ/x)",
    "explanation": "y=Asin(wt-2𝞹λ/x) is not an equation of a travelling wave(progressive wave) because the variable x cannot be in denominator\n(Lecture 3;09:27)",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> Progressive Wave (questions)",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "y =Asin(wt - kx)",
    "option_b": "x = 2Asin(wt-kx+𝚹)",
    "option_c": "y=Asin(wt-2𝞹λ/x)",
    "option_d": "y = Asin(2𝞹t/T + kx)",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 104
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "840904",
    "question": "A telescope has focal length of objective of 900mm, \nand 10 mm focal length of eyepiece, The meginification is :",
    "answer": "90x",
    "explanation": "m=fₒ/fₑ=900/10=90,\n90x",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Ray optics >> Magnification of telescope",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "100x",
    "option_b": "0.11x",
    "option_c": "1x",
    "option_d": "90x",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 105
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "830505",
    "question": "The inverse square law of intensity is valid for a:",
    "answer": "Point source",
    "explanation": "Intensity of a point source obeys the inverse square law.\n\nIntensity of a point light source is: I= Power/Area = P/4 𝜋 r² ⇒ I ∝ 1/r²",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Electromagnetic Waves >> Intensity of Electromagnetic Radiation",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Point source",
    "option_b": "Line source",
    "option_c": "Plane source",
    "option_d": "Cylinderical source",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 106
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222404",
    "question": "If the focal length of the lens is 10 cm then what is the power of the lens?",
    "answer": "10 D",
    "explanation": "p=1/10/100=10D (Lecture 6; 08:26)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Power of lens",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "10 D",
    "option_b": "11 D",
    "option_c": "12 D",
    "option_d": "13 D",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 107
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450278",
    "question": "Two identical piano wires, kept under the same tension  T  have a fundamental frequency of  600 Hz. The fractional increase in the tension of one  of the  wires  which will lead to  occurrence of  6 beats/s when both the wires oscillate together would be\n(2011)",
    "answer": "0.02",
    "explanation": "Step 1: fundamental frequency v,\nv = 1 / 2 L √ T / μ\n\n∴ ∆v / v = 1 / 2 ∆T / T\n∆ T / T =  2 × ∆ v / v\n           = 2 × 6 / 600 \n           = 0.02 \nvideo(AuFFjzfb4ks)",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 60",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "0.01",
    "option_b": "0.02",
    "option_c": "0.03",
    "option_d": "0.04",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 108
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181707",
    "question": "The currents in the same direction imply which force?",
    "answer": "attractive force",
    "explanation": "The currents in the same direction are equal to force attractive force.  (Lecture 4; 12:22)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Force between two conductor that are parallel",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "attractive force",
    "option_b": "repulsive force",
    "option_c": "both a & b",
    "option_d": "none of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 109
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "250911",
    "question": "What is the formula of the velocity of the hydrogen atom?",
    "answer": "Vo=2πke²/h",
    "explanation": "Vo=2πke²/h (Lecture 2; 24:43)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Atoms >> Bohr theory of H-atom",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Vo=2πke²/h",
    "option_b": "Vo=πke²/h",
    "option_c": "Vo=2πke²h",
    "option_d": "V=vo2/n",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 110
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222604",
    "question": "For the prism, for the small angle of incidence, we get a large_____?",
    "answer": "deviation",
    "explanation": "For the prism, for the small angle of incidence, we get a large deviation. (Lecture 7; 09:46)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Prism",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "deviation",
    "option_b": "diffraction",
    "option_c": "reflection",
    "option_d": "refraction",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 111
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "230608",
    "question": "According to Maxwell, Does the light or electromagnetic waves needs medium? Yes or no",
    "answer": "No",
    "explanation": "According to Maxwell, light need no medium for propagation.\nbecause light is an EM wave,  (Lecture 1; 01:56)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Wave Optics >> Theories",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "No",
    "option_b": "Yes",
    "option_c": "",
    "option_d": "",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 112
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "540301",
    "question": "At small angle A of a prism i. The minimum deviation is:",
    "answer": "δm=2arcsin(µA/2)-A",
    "explanation": "At minimum deviation:\nδm=2i-A, Snell's law:\nsini=µsin(r)=µsin(A/2),\nA is small,sin(A/2)=A/2\nthe, sin(δm+A/2)=µA/2\nThus, δm=2arcsin(µA/2)-A",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics and Optical instrument >> Set 51",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "δm=2arcsin(µA/2)-A",
    "option_b": "δm=2cot(µA/2)-A",
    "option_c": "δm=arcsin(µA/2)",
    "option_d": "δm=2sin(µA/2)-A",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 113
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "850205",
    "question": "In a Double slit experiment, two waves interfered on a screen, with the same intensity 𝐈₀, and a phase difference of 𝜋/2, The total intensity is:",
    "answer": "2𝐈₀",
    "explanation": "𝐈= 𝐈₁ + 𝐈₂ + 2√(𝐈₁𝐈₂) x cos(𝜑)\n𝐈=4𝐈₀cos²(𝜋/2),\nusing cos²(𝜋/2)=1/2(1+cos(𝜑)),\n=4𝐈₀cos²(𝜋/4)=2𝐈₀",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Wave optics >> Total intensity formula",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "2𝐈₀",
    "option_b": "4𝐈₀",
    "option_c": "6𝐈₀",
    "option_d": "𝐈₀",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 114
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450291",
    "question": "Two sound waves with wavelength 6 cm and 8 cm respectively, each propagate in a gas with velocity 240 m / s . We expect the following number of beats per minute. \n\n",
    "answer": "108 × 10³                                         ",
    "explanation": "Step 1: frequency = Velocity / wavelength\n∴ v₁ = V / λ₁ = 240 / 0.05 = 4800 Hz\nv₂ = V / λ₂  = 240 / 0.08  = 3000 Hz\n\nStep 2: Number of beats per second\nn = v₁ - v₂ = 4800 - 3000 = 1800 \n\nStep 3: Number of beats per minute =\nn × 60 = 1800 × 60 = 108 × 10³\n",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 64",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "208 × 10³",
    "option_b": "1600",
    "option_c": "1800",
    "option_d": "108 × 10³                                         ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 115
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "540251",
    "question": "In a projection lantern of focal length F, the object distance U is such that",
    "answer": "F<U<2F",
    "explanation": "The correct option is D as a projector produces a magnified,\nreal and inverted image of an object placed between F and 2F",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics and Optical instrument >> Set 38",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "U>2F>F",
    "option_b": "U<F<2F",
    "option_c": "U= F<2F",
    "option_d": "F<U<2F",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 116
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "830306",
    "question": "The magnetic field part of an electromagnetic wave in vacuum is\nB = cos[5y+5t] ĵ\nThe wavelength of this part of electromagnetic wave is\n\n",
    "answer": "2𝜋/5 m",
    "explanation": "Given, \nB = cos[5y+5t] ĵ...(i)\n\nComparing (i) with the equation\nB=Bₒcos(ky + ωt)\n\nk = 5 m⁻¹,\nB₀ = 1 T, \nc = 3 × 10⁸ m s⁻¹\nω = 5 rads⁻¹\n\nThus, λ = 2𝜋/k \nλ = 2𝜋/5 m",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Electromagnetic Waves >> Equation of sinusoidal Magnetic field",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "𝜋 m",
    "option_b": "4𝜋/5 m",
    "option_c": "𝜋/5 m",
    "option_d": "2𝜋/5 m",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 117
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222017",
    "question": "A glass dumbbell of length 30 cm and refractive index 1.5 has ends of radius of curvature 3 cm. Find the position of the image due to refraction at one end only, when the object is situated in air at a distance of 12 cm from one end of the dumbbell along the axis.",
    "answer": "18 cm",
    "explanation": "Step 1; µ₂/v - µ₁/u=µ₂-µ₁/R  \nstep 2; 1.5/v-1/(12)=0.5/3 cm,    1.5/v=1/6-1/12=1/12,\nstep 3; v=18cm (Lecture 4; 17:19)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Refraction at a spherical surface",
    "difficulty_level": "2",
    "option_a": "18 cm",
    "option_b": "19 cm",
    "option_c": "20 cm",
    "option_d": "21 cm",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 118
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222403",
    "question": "What is the SI unit of power of a lens?",
    "answer": "dioptre",
    "explanation": "The SI unit of power of a lens is dioptre. (Lecture 6; 08:08)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Power of lens",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "dioptre",
    "option_b": "m",
    "option_c": "m/s",
    "option_d": "kg/m",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 119
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "450214",
    "question": "An air column, closed at one end and open at the other, resonates with a tuning fork when the smallest length of the column is 30 cm. The third larger length of the column resonating with the same tuning fork  is",
    "answer": "750 cm",
    "explanation": "Step 1: harmonic position for positive nodes are \nx = λ / 4 , 3λ / 4, 5λ / 4, 7λ / 4 and so on\n\nStep 2: \nFirst harmonic is obtained at \nL = λ / 4 = 30 cm\n\nStep 3: \nThird harmonic is obtained for resonance,\nL' = 5 λ / 4 = 5 × 150 = 750 cm\n\n",
    "topic_name": "Class 11 Physics >> Waves >> set 38",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "100 cm",
    "option_b": "150 cm",
    "option_c": "450 cm",
    "option_d": "750 cm",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 120
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "221601",
    "question": "When an incident ray enters the glass slab from a rarer medium to the denser than it gets?",
    "answer": "Refracted",
    "explanation": "When a incident ray enters into the glass slab then it gets refracted. (Lecture 2; 14:22)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Glass slab",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "Refracted",
    "option_b": "Reflected",
    "option_c": "Both a & b",
    "option_d": "None of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 121
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "811306",
    "question": "A solenoid produces a magnetic field of 8T when in circuit. What is the energy per unit volume of this solenoid?",
    "answer": "2.5x10⁷J/m³",
    "explanation": "The formula to calculate the Magnetic Energy density is:U=B²/2𝞵₀\nWe are given B=8T  𝞵₀=4𝛑x10⁻⁷H/m\nThen we have U=B²/2𝞵₀,\nU=(8)²/(2x4𝛑x10⁻⁷)\nU=(64)/(8𝛑x10⁻⁷)\nU=2.5x10⁷J/m³",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Electromagnetic Induction >> Magnetic Energy",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "10⁷J/m³",
    "option_b": "10⁻⁷J/m³",
    "option_c": "5x10⁻⁷J/m³",
    "option_d": "2.5x10⁷J/m³",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 122
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "540332",
    "question": "A thin prism of angle 15° made of glass of refractive index µ₁ = 1.5 is combined with another prism of glass of refractive index µ₂ = 1.75. \nThe combination of the prisms produces dispersion without deviation. The angle of the second prism should be",
    "answer": "10°",
    "explanation": "For dispersion without deviation \nδ1 + δ2 = 0\n(δ1 – 1)A1 + (µ₂ – 1) A2 = 0 \nA2= -(µ₁ – 1)A1  / (µ₂ – 1)\nSubstituting the given values, we get\nA2= (1.5-1)15 / (1.75-1) = -10\nNegative sign shows that two prisms \nmust be joined in opposition\n\nvideo(UVk__tjDQ3c)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics and Optical instrument >> Set 59",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "5°",
    "option_b": "7°",
    "option_c": "10°",
    "option_d": "12°",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 123
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "820504",
    "question": "Calculate the impedance of a circuit at a frequency,w of 100𝝅 having a capacitor of value 16𝜇F, an inductor of value 1H and a resistor of 100𝛀",
    "answer": "152𝛀",
    "explanation": "The formula to calculate the impedance of an RLC series circuit is: Z=√(R² + (Xₗ-Xc)² )\nGiven w=100𝝅 ,  C=16𝜇F=16x10⁻⁶F,  L=1H,   R=100𝛀   and Z=?\nWe determine Xₗ=wL=100𝝅 x1=100𝝅=314𝛀    and  Xc=1/Cw=1/16x10⁻⁶x100𝝅=200𝛀   \nZ=√(R² + (Xₗ-Xc)² )\nZ=√(100² + (314-200)² )\nZ=152𝛀",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Alternating Current >> Impedance of an RLC series circuit",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "15𝛀",
    "option_b": "52𝛀",
    "option_c": "102𝛀",
    "option_d": "152𝛀",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 124
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "880806",
    "question": "Suppose the no. of electrons in an atom is n. The no. of neutrons in is 2 more than the no. of electrons. If the binding energy per nucleon is 20MeV and total binding energy is 6 times the binding energy per nucleon, calculate the value of n. ",
    "answer": "2",
    "explanation": "No. of protons = No. of electrons\nNo. of protons = n\n\nNo. of neutrons= n +2\n\nMass number= No. of protons + No. of neutrons\nMass number= n+ n + 2\nmass number= 2n + 2\n\nEbn = Eb / A\n20MeV= 120MeV / A\nA=6\n\nTherefore, \n2n+2= 6 \nn=2",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Nuclei >> Binding energy per nucleon",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "1",
    "option_b": "2",
    "option_c": "3",
    "option_d": "4",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "corrected",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 125
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222802",
    "question": "What is the formula of magnification of simple microscope if the image is at LDDV?",
    "answer": "m=D/x",
    "explanation": "m=D/x\nWhere, D is the near distance of the image\nx is object distance\n (Lecture 8; 07:00)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> simple microscope",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "m=D/x",
    "option_b": "m=1+D/f",
    "option_c": "m=D/f",
    "option_d": "m=β/α",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 126
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "490331",
    "question": "A galvanometer of resistance, G, is shunted by a resistance S ohm. To keep the main current in the circuit unchanged, the resistance to be put in series with the galvanometer is",
    "answer": "G²/(𝑆+G)",
    "explanation": "Step 1: Let resistance R is to be put in series with galvanometer G to keep the main current\nin the circuit unchanged.\n\nStep 2:\n∴ 𝐺𝑆/(𝐺 + 𝑆) + 𝑅 = 𝐺\n𝑅 = 𝐺 − 𝐺𝑆/(𝐺 + 𝑆) ⇒ 𝑅 = (𝐺² + 𝐺𝑆 − 𝐺𝑆)/(𝐺 + 𝑆)\n= 𝐺²/(𝐺 + S)\n\nvideo(qE18wnjc3Pc)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Set 72",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "𝐺/(𝑆+G)",
    "option_b": "S²/(𝑆+G)",
    "option_c": "S𝐺/(𝑆+G)",
    "option_d": "G²/(𝑆+G)",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 127
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "181803",
    "question": "Consider a loop placed between two poles in the system shown in the diagram what is the direction of the force for AB? (n1806)",
    "answer": "inwards",
    "explanation": "Since the magnetic force is prependicular to the direction of magentic field and length, it will be in inward direction. (Lecture 4; 14:49) diagram (ne1806)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Loop",
    "difficulty_level": "3",
    "option_a": "inwards",
    "option_b": "outwards",
    "option_c": "left",
    "option_d": "right",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 128
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "540254",
    "question": "A piano convex lens is made of refractive index 1.6. \nThe radius of curvature of the curved surface is 120m. \nThe focal length of the lens is",
    "answer": "200 cm",
    "explanation": "We have :r₁ = +∞, r₂ = – 120 cm                                                                                       \n1/f= (μ -1)[1/r₁ -1/r₂]                                                                                                \n =(1.6 -1)[1/ ∞ -1/-120]                                                                                                                 \nF= 200cm          ",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics and Optical instrument >> Set 39",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "200 cm",
    "option_b": "400 cm",
    "option_c": "100 cm",
    "option_d": "600 cm",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 129
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "821205",
    "question": "Determine the maximum amplitude of  the electric field of an electromagnetic wave whose average energy wave density is (8x10⁻⁴)Wm⁻².Given 𝜀₀=8.85x10⁻¹²C²N⁻¹m⁻²",
    "answer": "1.34x10⁴N/C",
    "explanation": "The formula to calculate the average Energy density of an electromagnetic(EM) wave is :<u>=(1/2)𝜺₀E₀²\ngiven 𝜀₀=8.85x10⁻¹²C²N⁻¹m⁻², <u>=(8x10⁻⁴)Wm⁻² and E₀=? \n<u>=(1/2)𝜺₀E₀² \n8x10⁻⁴=(1/2)(8.85x10⁻¹²)(E₀)² \n8x10⁻⁴=(4.425x10⁻¹²)(E₀)² \n8=(4.425x10⁻⁸)(E₀)² \n(E₀)²=(8/4.425)x10⁸ \n(E₀)²=1.8x10⁸ \nE₀=1.34x10⁴N/C",
    "topic_name": "Physical Formulae >> Alternating Current >> Average energy density of Electromagnetic  wave",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "24x10⁸ N/C",
    "option_b": "1.34x10⁴N/C",
    "option_c": "𝜺₀x10⁸ N/C",
    "option_d": "13.4x10⁴N/C",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 130
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "490250",
    "question": " If a long hollow copper pipe carries a current, then produced magnetic field will be ",
    "answer": "outside the pipe only ",
    "explanation": "Use Ampère’s law ∮ 𝐵. 𝑑𝑙 = 𝜇₀𝑖𝑒𝑛𝑐𝑙𝑜𝑠𝑒𝑑\nOutside 𝑖𝑒𝑛𝑐𝑙𝑜𝑠𝑒𝑑 ≠ 0(𝑠𝑜𝑚𝑒 𝑣𝑎𝑙𝑢𝑒) ⇒ 𝐵 ≠ 0\nInside 𝑖𝑒𝑛𝑐𝑙𝑜𝑠𝑒𝑑 = 0(𝑠𝑜𝑚𝑒 𝑣𝑎𝑙𝑢𝑒) ⇒ 𝐵 = 0\n\nvideo(E2As9Aw1zHo)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Magnetic effects of electric current >> Set 45",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "both inside and outside the pipe ",
    "option_b": "outside the pipe only ",
    "option_c": "inside the pipe only ",
    "option_d": "neither inside nor outside the pipe. ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 131
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222011",
    "question": "If the image distance is negative then the image will be?",
    "answer": "virtual image",
    "explanation": "If the image distance is negative then the image will be virtual. (Lecture 4; 03:48)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Spherical lenses",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "virtual image",
    "option_b": "real image",
    "option_c": "both a & b",
    "option_d": "none of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 132
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "231104",
    "question": "What is the formula of the position of any bright fringe of the constructive interference?",
    "answer": "x=nλ D/d",
    "explanation": "x=nλ D/d\nwhere d is the size of the slit, λ  is the wavelength\nD is the distance between the slit and the screen (Lecture 3; 06:26)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Wave Optics >> Fringe width",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "x=nλ D/d",
    "option_b": "P=nλ ",
    "option_c": "p=dsinθ",
    "option_d": "x=(2n-1)λ D/2d",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 133
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "222012",
    "question": "If the height of the object is negative then the image would be?",
    "answer": "real image",
    "explanation": "If the height of the object is negative then the image would be real. (Lecture 4; 04:37)",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics >> Spherical lenses",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "virtual image",
    "option_b": "real image",
    "option_c": "both a & b",
    "option_d": "none of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 134
  },
  {
    "unique_id": "540215",
    "question": "If the magnification of a virtual image formed of an object 10cm from a convex lens is 3, the focal length of the lens is",
    "answer": "15cm",
    "explanation": "Using the magnification formula:\nm=u/v=f/u-f   \n=3(10-f) =f                                                                                \n f=15cm                                ",
    "topic_name": "Class 12 Physics >> Ray optics and Optical instrument >> Set 29",
    "difficulty_level": "1",
    "option_a": "10cm",
    "option_b": "15cm",
    "option_c": "16cm",
    "option_d": "19cm",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "clue_1": "",
    "clue_2": "",
    "clue_3": "",
    "id": 135
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 51048,
    "question": "What is the ratio fo urms and ump for oxygen at 298K?",
    "answer": 1.224,
    "explanation": "The ratio of root mean square speed, represented as urms to the most probable speed, represented as ump is always the same for identical conditions and same gas. It is √3RT/M / √8RT/πM = 1.224.\nReference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 147; Paragraph 3)",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> States of matter >> Most Challenging Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": 1.124,
    "option_b": 1.224,
    "option_c": 1.228,
    "option_d": 1.128,
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 136
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 21205,
    "question": "Select the incorrect statements regarding emission spectra: \n \n (a) The spectrum of the visible light is discrete as all wavelengths (red to violet) of the visible light are represented in the spectra.\n \n (b) The emission spectra of atoms in the gas phase do not show a continuous spread of wavelength from red to violet, rather they emit light only at specific wavelengths with dark spaces between them. \n \n (c) The spectra with visible lines separated by dark spaces between them are called line spectra or atomic spectra because the emitted radiation is identified by the appearance of bright lines in the spectra.\n (d) Different elements may have asimilar line emission spectrum.\n (e) The characteristic lines in atomic spectra can be used in chemical analysis to identify unknown atoms.\n (f) The element helium (He) was discovered in the sun by spectroscopic method.\n \n Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:",
    "answer": "(a) and (d) only",
    "explanation": "The spectrum of the visible light is continuous as all wavelengths (red to violet) of the visible light are represented in the spectra. The emission spectra of atoms in the gas phase, on the other hand, do not show a continuous spread of wavelength from red to violet, rather they emit light only at specific wavelengths with dark spaces between them. Such spectra are called line spectra or atomic spectra because the emitted radiation is identified by the appearance of bright lines in the spectra. Line emission spectra are of great interest in the study of electronic structure. Each element has a unique line emission spectrum. The characteristic lines in atomic spectra can be used in chemical analysis to identify unknown atoms in the same way as fingerprints are used to identify people. The exact matching of lines of the emission spectrum of the atoms of a known element with the lines from an unknown sample quickly establishes the identity of the latter.\"\n\"The element helium (He) was discovered in the sun by spectroscopic method.\"\nReference; NCERT class 11; Page no.44; Paragraph 4, 5, 6)",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Structure of atom >> Developments leading to the Bohr's model of atom - Evidence for the quantized Electronic Energy Levels: Atomic spectra",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "(a), (b) and (f) only",
    "option_b": "(b) and (e) only",
    "option_c": "(a) and (d) only",
    "option_d": "(b), (c), (d) and (f) only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 137
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 221312,
    "question": "What is the change in the oxidation state of nitrogen in the following reaction?                    NH₄⁺ + 3 O₂ → N₂ + 6 H2O",
    "answer": 5,
    "explanation": "Explanation: In the given reaction, nitrogen (N) changes its oxidation state from -3 in NH₄⁺to 0 in N₂, indicating an increase of 5 units. Hence, the change in the oxidation state of nitrogen is +5. (Reference- NCERT Chemistry Class 11 (Part 2); Page 267;Paragraph 8.3)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Redox Reactions >> Exercise Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": -3,
    "option_b": -1,
    "option_c": 3,
    "option_d": 5,
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 138
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 250501,
    "question": "Alcohols can be prepared from the following method(s)?",
    "answer": "All of the above",
    "explanation": "Alcohols are prepared by the following methods: From alkenes, From carbonyl compounds, From Grignard reagents.\n(Reference: NCERT Chemistry Class 12; Page 329; Paragraph No. 3)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Alcohols, Phenols and Ether >> Alcohols and Phenols",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Alkenes",
    "option_b": "Carbonyl Compounds",
    "option_c": "Grignard Reagents",
    "option_d": "All of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 139
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 21401,
    "question": "The French physicist, _______ , in _______ proposed that matter, like radiation, should also exhibit dual behaviour i.e., both particle and wavelike properties.",
    "answer": "Louis de Broglie, 1924",
    "explanation": "The French physicist, de Broglie, in 1924 proposed that matter, like radiation, should also exhibit dual behaviour i.e., both particle and wavelike properties.\"\n\nReference; NCERT class 11; Page no.49; Paragraph 2",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Structure of atom >> Towards quantum mechanical model of the atom",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Louis de Broglie, 1924",
    "option_b": "Werner Heisenberg, 1926",
    "option_c": "Bohr, 1906",
    "option_d": "Heinrich Hertz,1918",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 140
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 220501,
    "question": "Oxidation number of a particular element in compounds can be -",
    "answer": "all of these",
    "explanation": "Sometimes, we come across with certain compounds in which the oxidation number of a particular element in the compound is in fraction.(Reference- NCERT Chemistry Class 11 (Part 2); Page 273; The Paradox of Fractional Oxidation Number)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Redox Reactions >> Paradox of Fractional Oxidation number",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "natural number",
    "option_b": 0,
    "option_c": "fraction",
    "option_d": "all of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 141
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 10104,
    "question": "Elixir of life’ is supposed to grant________.",
    "answer": "Immortality",
    "explanation": "‘Elixir of life’ would grant immortality.\n \n Reference: (NCERT Class-11 Page- 1 Paragraph-2)",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Some basic concepts of chemistry >> Development of Chemistry",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Mortality",
    "option_b": "Immortality",
    "option_c": "Immense muscular strength",
    "option_d": "None of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 142
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 121053,
    "question": "Justify the statement: \"Among the resonance structures, the one which has all the atoms with octet of electrons\".",
    "answer": "Less separation of opposite charges and more dispersal of charge are more stable",
    "explanation": "Among the resonance structures, the one which has all the atoms with octet of electrons (except hydrogen which has a duplet), less separation of opposite charges and more dispersal of charge are more stable. Reference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 354; Paragraph No. 3 )",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> Electron movement and effects",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "More separation of same charges and less dispersal of charge are less stable",
    "option_b": "More separation of opposite charges and more dispersal of charge are less stable",
    "option_c": "Less separation of same charges and less dispersal of charge are more stable",
    "option_d": "Less separation of opposite charges and more dispersal of charge are more stable",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 143
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 21302,
    "question": "The postulates which constitutes the basis of Bohr’s model for hydrogen atom are:\n \n (i) The electron in the hydrogen atom can move around the nucleus in a circular path of fixed radius and energy. These paths are called orbits.\n \n (ii) Orbits are arranged concentrically around the nucleus.\n \n (iii) Orbits are arranged linearly around the nucleus.\n \n (iv) The energy of an electron in the orbit changes with time.\n \n (v) The electron will move from a lower stationary state to a higher stationary state when required amount of energy is absorbed by the electron or energy is emitted when electron moves from higher stationary state to lower stationary state.\n \n (vi) The energy change take place in a continuous manner between orbits.\n \n (vii) The frequency of radiation is absorbed or emitted according to Bohr’s frequency rule i.e., when transition occurs between two stationary states that differ in energy by ∆E, is given by:\n \n v = ∆E/h = (E₂ - E₁)/h\n \n where E₁ and E₂ are the energies of the lower and higher allowed energy states respectively.\n \n (viii) The angular momentum of an electron is quantised. In a given stationary state it can be expressed as in equation \n \n mₑvr = nh/2π, n = 1,2,3..... \n \n where mₑ is the mass of electron, v is the velocity and r is the radius of the orbit in which electron is moving.\n \n (ix) An electron can move only in those orbits for which its angular momentum is the fraction of h/2π.\n \n Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:",
    "answer": "(i), (ii), (v), (vii), and (viii)",
    "explanation": "Bohr’s model for hydrogen atom is based on the following postulates:\n\n(i) The electron in the hydrogen atom can move around the nucleus in a circular path of fixed radius and energy. These paths are called orbits, stationary states or allowed energy states. These orbits are arranged concentrically around the nucleus.\n\n(ii) The energy of an electron in the orbit does not change with time. However, the electron will move from a lower stationary state to a higher stationary state when required amount of energy is absorbed by the electron or energy is emitted when electron moves from higher stationary state to lower stationary state. The energy change does not take place in a continuous manner.\n\n(iii) The frequency of radiation absorbed or emitted when transition occurs between two stationary states that differ in energy by ∆E, is given by:\n\nv = ∆E/h = (E₂ - E₁)/h\n\nwhere E₁ and E₂ are the energies of the lower and higher allowed energy states respectively. This expression is commonly known as Bohr’s frequency rule.\n\n(iv) The angular momentum of an electron is quantised. In a given stationary state it can be expressed as in equation \n\nmₑvr = nh/2π, n = 1,2,3..... \n\nwhere mₑ is the mass of electron, v is the velocity and r is the radius of the orbit in which electron is moving. Thus an electron can move only in those orbits for which its angular momentum is integral multiple of h/2π. That means angular momentum is quantised.\"\n\nReference; NCERT class 11; Page no.46; Paragraph 3, 4, 5, 6)\nReference; NCERT class 11; Page no.47; Paragraph 1, 2)",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Structure of atom >> Bohr's model for hydrogen atom",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "(i), (ii), (vi), (vii), and (viii)",
    "option_b": "(i), (iii), (v), and (viii)",
    "option_c": "(i), (ii), (iii), (iv), (v), (vi), (vii), and (viii)",
    "option_d": "(i), (ii), (v), (vii), and (viii)",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 144
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 11127,
    "question": "The number of Oxygen atoms in 4.4 g of CO₂ is-",
    "answer": "1.2 × 10²³",
    "explanation": "1 mol of CO₂ = 44 g of CO₂,\n \n 4.4 g CO₂ = 0.1 mol CO₂= 6 × 10²² molecules = 2 × 6 × 10²² atoms of O = 1.2 × 10²³ atoms of O.\n \n NEET 1989\n \n Reference: (NCERT Class-11 Page- 18 Paragraph-4)",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Some basic concepts of chemistry >> Previous Year Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "1.2 × 10²³",
    "option_b": "6 × 10²²",
    "option_c": "6 × 10²³",
    "option_d": "12 × 10²³",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 145
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120945,
    "question": "The reactive site is _________ portion of the molecule.",
    "answer": "Electron deficient",
    "explanation": "The reactive site may be electron deficient portion of the molecule (a positive reactive site) e.g., an atom with incomplete electron shell or the positive end of the dipole in the molecule. Reference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 351; Paragraph No. 1)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> Concepts in organic reaction mechanism",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Electron efficient",
    "option_b": "Electron deficient",
    "option_c": "Neutral",
    "option_d": "All of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 146
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 261910,
    "question": "Assertion: Dry hydrogen chloride increases the electrophilicity of the carbonyl carbon during the reaction of aldehydes or ketones with alcohols.\n\nReason: Dry hydrogen chloride protonates the oxygen atom of the carbonyl compound.",
    "answer": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "Dry hydrogen chloride protonates the oxygen of the carbonyl compounds and therefore, increases the electrophilicity of the carbonyl carbon facilitating the reaction with alcohols.",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Aldehydes,ketones & carboxylic acids >> Assertion & Reason Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is not the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but reason is false",
    "option_d": "Both Assertion and reason is false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 147
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130721,
    "question": "Consider the reaction given below in diagram?(n1372)",
    "answer": "a",
    "explanation": "A nitro group is introduced into benzene ring when benzene is heated with a mixture of concentrated nitric acid and concentrated sulphuric acid (nitrating mixture).\n\nReference: (NCERT Chemistry Class-11, Page-400, Paragraph -4)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Hydrocarbon >> Aromatic Hydrocarbons",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "a",
    "option_b": "b",
    "option_c": "c",
    "option_d": "d",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 148
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 22402,
    "question": "Be²⁺ is isoelectronic with which of the following ions?",
    "answer": "Li⁺",
    "explanation": "Isoelectronic species means species having same number of electrons. \n\nAmong the given options, Be⁺² is isoelectronic with Li⁺. Both contain 2 electrons. \n\nThey have electronic configuration of, Be⁺² = 1s² = Li⁺\n\nWhereas, no. of electrons in other given species are:\n\nH⁺ = 0, Na⁺ = 10, Mg²⁺ = 10\n\nReference; NEET; 2014",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Structure of atom >> Previous year question",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "H⁺",
    "option_b": "Li⁺",
    "option_c": "Na⁺",
    "option_d": "Mg²⁺",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 149
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 131002,
    "question": "Arrange the halogens F₂ , Cl₂ , Br₂ , I₂  in order of their increasing\nreactivity with alkanes.",
    "answer": "I₂ < Br₂ < Cl₂ < F₂",
    "explanation": "As we go down the group in the periodic table, the size of the halogen atom increases, and its ability to form a bond with the carbon atom in the alkane molecule decreases. Hence, the reactivity of halogens with alkanes increases as we move from fluorine to iodine.",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Hydrocarbon >> Exemplar Based Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Cl₂ < F₂ < I₂ < Br₂",
    "option_b": "F₂ < Cl₂ < Br₂ < I₂",
    "option_c": "I₂ < Br₂ < Cl₂ < F₂",
    "option_d": "Br₂ < I₂ < F₂ < Cl₂",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 150
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 40233,
    "question": "Choose an appropriate option for the given statement: \"The formation of a negative ion from a halogen atom and a positive ion from an alkali metal atom is associated with",
    "answer": "Gain and loss of electron",
    "explanation": "The formation of a negative ion from a halogen atom and a positive ion from an alkali metal atom is associated with the gain and loss of an electron by the respective atoms. \n\nReference: (NCERT chemistry Class 11; page 101; paragraph no.4)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Chemical bonding and molecular structure >> Kossel-lewis approach",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Gain and loss of electron",
    "option_b": "Generation of free radical",
    "option_c": "Sharing of alternate proton",
    "option_d": "Sharing of alternate bond",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 151
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 240612,
    "question": "Solubility of haloalkane in water is",
    "answer": "Slightly soluble",
    "explanation": "The haloalkanes are very slightly soluble in water. \n\nIn order to dissolve haloalkane in water, energy is required to overcome the attractions between the haloalkane molecules and break the hydrogen bonds between water molecules. \n\n(Reference: NCERT Chemistry Class 12 Pg 299 Paragraph 2)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Haloalkanes and Haloarenes >> Physical Properties",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Soluble",
    "option_b": "Slightly soluble",
    "option_c": "Insoluble",
    "option_d": "Both A and B",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 152
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 560233,
    "question": "Which of the following does not react with benzene sulphonyl chloride?\n\nshown in the diagram (56232)",
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "",
    "topic_name": "Organic Named Reaction >> Class 12 >> Hinsberg's",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "A",
    "option_b": "B",
    "option_c": "C",
    "option_d": "D",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 153
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 11101,
    "question": "The dimensions of pressure are the same as that of?",
    "answer": "Energy per unit volume.",
    "explanation": "Pressure = Force/ Area, Therefore, dimensions of pressure = MLT⁻²/L² = ML⁻¹T⁻²\n \n Dimensions of energy per unit volume = Energy/ Volume = ML²T⁻²/ L³ = ML⁻¹T⁻²\n \n For Energy per unit volume, work out the dimensions of work done using Force and displacement.\n \n NEET 1995\n \n Reference: (NCERT Class-11 Page-13 Last topic)",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Some basic concepts of chemistry >> Previous Year Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Force per unit volume.",
    "option_b": "Energy per unit volume.",
    "option_c": "Force",
    "option_d": "Energy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 154
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 100776,
    "question": "What is the use of Cu-Be alloys?",
    "answer": "High strength springs",
    "explanation": "Copper - Beryllium alloys are used in the preparation of high strength springs.\n\n(Reference- NCERT Chemistry Class 11 (Part 2); Page 308; Paragraph 10.6.7)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> The s Block Elements >> Group 2 Elements- Properties and Uses",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "High strength springs",
    "option_b": "Windows of X-ray tube",
    "option_c": "Aircraft",
    "option_d": "Radiotherapy",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 155
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 260218,
    "question": "The carbonyl carbon is a ______?",
    "answer": "Electron acceptor",
    "explanation": "The carbonyl carbon is an electrophilic (Lewis acid), and carbonyl oxygen, a nucleophilic (Lewis base) centre. \n\nReference : (NCERT - Class 12 Page-361 Paragraph-2)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Aldehydes,ketones & carboxylic acids >> Nomenclature and Structure of Carbonyl Group",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Carbocation",
    "option_b": "Electron donor",
    "option_c": "Electron acceptor",
    "option_d": "Carbanion",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 156
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 251210,
    "question": "Which of the following reaction will form an alkene? Refer diagram(n25104)",
    "answer": "c",
    "explanation": "When the vapours of primary or  secondary alcohol are passed over heated copper at 573 K, dehydrogenation takes place and aldehyde or ketone is formed.\n\nTertiary alcohols undergo dehydration forming alkenes\n\n(Reference: NCERT Chemistry Class 12; Page 340; Paragraph No. 5). Refer diagram(ne2586)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Alcohols, Phenols and Ether >> NCERT Reactions",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "a",
    "option_b": "b",
    "option_c": "c",
    "option_d": "both b and c",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 157
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 290302,
    "question": "Step growth polymerisation is",
    "answer": "condensation polymerisation",
    "explanation": "There are two broad types of polymerisation reactions, i.e., the addition or chain growth polymerisation and condensation or step growth polymerisation.\n \n Reference : (NCERT Class-12 Page- 434 Paragraph-3)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Polymers >> Types of polymerisation reactions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "chain growth polymerisation",
    "option_b": "condensation polymerisation",
    "option_c": "addition polymerisation",
    "option_d": "all of the above",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 158
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 22311,
    "question": "Electromagnetic radiation of wavelength 242 nm is just sufficient to ionise the sodium atom. Calculate the ionisation energy of sodium in kJ mol⁻¹.",
    "answer": "494 kJ",
    "explanation": "The ionization energy of sodium will be equal to the energy possessed by the radiation of wavelength 242 nm. The ionization energy of 1 Na atom is,\n Eᵢₒₙ = hc / λ = (6.626 × 10⁻³⁴ Js)(3.0 × 10⁸ ms⁻¹) / 242 x 10⁻⁹ m = 8.21 × 10⁻¹⁹ J \n The ionization energy per mole of Na is = 8.21 × 10⁻¹⁹ J x 6.023 × 10²³ = 494000 J = 494 kJ\"   \nReference; NCERT class 11; Page no. 69; Exercise question 2.10",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Structure of atom >> NCERT exercise",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "4940 kJ",
    "option_b": "49.4 kJ",
    "option_c": "49400 kJ",
    "option_d": "494 kJ",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 159
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 131008,
    "question": "Arrange the following alkyl halides in decreasing order of the rate of β  − elimination reaction with alcoholic KOH. Refer diagram(n13138)",
    "answer": "A > C > B",
    "explanation": "The rate of b-elimination reaction with alcoholic KOH depends on the stability of the carbocation intermediate that is formed during the reaction. The more stable the carbocation intermediate, the faster the rate of the reaction.",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Hydrocarbon >> Exemplar Based Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "A>B>C",
    "option_b": "C > B > A",
    "option_c": "B > C > A",
    "option_d": "A > C > B",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 160
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120640,
    "question": "What is the IUPAC name of Cl₂CHCH₂OH?",
    "answer": "2,2-Dichloroethan-1-ol",
    "explanation": "Lowest locant rule is applied to give lowest number to functional group. Reference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 344; Paragraph No. 2)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> Nomenclature of organic compounds with functional group",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "2,2-Dichloroethan-1-ol",
    "option_b": "2,2-Dual Chlorine ethanol",
    "option_c": "1, 1-dichloro-2-ethanol",
    "option_d": "none of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 161
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 121518,
    "question": "Increasing order of stability among the eclipse, anti, gauche of 2-fluoroethanol is :[AIEEE 2006]",
    "answer": "Gauche,Eclipse,Anti",
    "explanation": "Gauche is most stable because of H- bonding between F and OH group. Refer diagram(e1217) .",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> JEE Mains",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Ecipse,Gauche, Anti",
    "option_b": "Gauche,Eclipse,Anti",
    "option_c": "Eclipse,Anti, Gauche",
    "option_d": "Anti, Gauche, Eclipse",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 162
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 101402,
    "question": "Which of the alkali metal chloride (MCl) form its dihydrate salt (MCl.2H₂O) easily?",
    "answer": "LiCl",
    "explanation": "LiCl is deliquescent and crystallises as a hydrate, LiCl.2H2O whereas other alkali metal chlorides do not form hydrates.\n\n(Reference- NCERT Chemistry Class 11 (Part 2); Page 304; Paragraph 10.3.1(USES))\n[NEET-2019 (Odisha)]",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> The s Block Elements >> Previous Year Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "KCl",
    "option_b": "LiCl",
    "option_c": "CsCl",
    "option_d": "RbCl",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 163
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 271608,
    "question": "Assertion: Tertiary amines do not react with benzenesulphonyl chloride, which is used for the distinction and separation of primary, secondary, and tertiary amines.\n\nReason: Benzenesulphonyl chloride is replaced by p-phenylsulphonyl chloride these days.",
    "answer": "Assertion is true but reason is false",
    "explanation": "Tertiary aminses do not react with Hinsberg reagent. \"These days benzenesulphonyl chloride is replaced by p-toluenesulphonyl chloride. \nReference: (NCERT class-12; Page No. 401; Paragraph No. 5)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic Compounds Containing Nitrogen >> Assertion Reason Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is not the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but reason is false",
    "option_d": "Assertion is false but reason is true",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 164
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 40101,
    "question": "No elements can exist independently except:",
    "answer": "Noble gases",
    "explanation": "Noble gases have completely filled valance shell.\n\nAn atom bonds with other atoms to completely fill its valance shell. \n\nThe valence shell of Noble gases are already filled, so they exist independently. \n\nReference: (NCERT chemistry Class 11; page 100; paragraph no.1)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Chemical bonding and molecular structure >> Introduction",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Alkali metals",
    "option_b": "Halogens",
    "option_c": "Noble gases",
    "option_d": "Chalcogens",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 165
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 101444,
    "question": "Which one of the following is present as an active ingredient in bleaching powder for bleaching action",
    "answer": "Ca(OCl)₂",
    "explanation": "Active ingredient in bleaching powder for bleaching action is Ca(OCl)₂.\n\n(Reference- NCERT Chemistry Class 11 (Part 2); Page 311; Paragraph slaked lime) \n\n[AIPMT 2011]",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> The s Block Elements >> Previous Year Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "CaOCl₂",
    "option_b": "Ca(OCl)₂",
    "option_c": "CaO₂Cl",
    "option_d": "CaCl₂",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 166
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 40509,
    "question": "Which statement is wrong regarding the conditions to write Lewis-Langmuir theory\n\na. The Lewis-Langmuir theory can be understood by considering the formation of the chlorine molecule, Cl2. \n\nb. The Cl atom with electronic configuration, [Ne]3s2 3p5, is one electron short of the Neon configuration.\n\nc. The formation of the Cl2 molecule can be understood in terms of the transfering of a pair of electrons from the one chlorine to another atom, each chlorine atom contributing 8 electrons to the shared pair.\n\nd.  In the process both chlorine atoms attain the outer shell octet of the nearest noble gas (i.e., argon).",
    "answer": "Only b and c",
    "explanation": "The Lewis-Langmuir theory can be understood by considering the formation of the chlorine molecule, Cl2. \n\nThe Cl atom with electronic configuration, [Ne]3s2 3p5, is one electron short of the argon configuration. \n\nThe formation of the Cl2 molecule can be understood in terms of the sharing of a pair of electrons between the two chlorine atoms, each chlorine atom contributing one electron to the shared pair. \n\nIn the process both chlorine atoms attain the outer shell octet of the nearest noble gas (i.e., argon). \n\nReference: (NCERT chemistry Class 11; page 102; paragraph no.4)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Chemical bonding and molecular structure >> Covalent bond",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Only a and c",
    "option_b": "Only b",
    "option_c": "Only b and c",
    "option_d": "Only a and d",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 167
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 21808,
    "question": "Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion(A) and the other is labelled as Reason(R).\n \n AssertionA): The size, shape and energy of the three p orbitals are not identical.\n \n Reason(R): The lobes of the p-orbitals do not lie along the x, y or z axis.\n \n In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:",
    "answer": "Both (A) and (R) are false.",
    "explanation": "The size, shape and energy of the three p-orbitals are identical. They differ however, in the way the lobes are oriented. Since the lobes may be considered to lie along the x, y or z axis, they are given the designations 2pₓ, 2pᵧ, and 2p_z.\"\n\nReference; NCERT class 11; Page no.59; Paragraph 1",
    "topic_name": "Physical Chemistry >> Structure of atom >> Quantum mechanical model of atom - Shapes of Atomic Orbitals",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
    "option_b": "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
    "option_c": "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
    "option_d": "Both (A) and (R) are false.",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 168
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 130884,
    "question": "Which of the following compounds will be most easily attacked by an electrophile, refer diagram?(n13114)",
    "answer": "a",
    "explanation": ": —OH, —Cl and —CH₃ groups in benzene are ortho, para directing groups. \n\nBut among these —OH group is strongly activating while —CH₃ is weakly activating and —Cl is deactivating. \n\nThus, phenol will be most easily attacked by an electrophile.\n\nReference: (NCERT Chemistry Class-11, Page-403, Paragraph -4)\n(NEET 1998,1999)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Hydrocarbon >> Previous Year Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "a",
    "option_b": "b",
    "option_c": "c",
    "option_d": "d",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 169
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120662,
    "question": "Heptanal indicates the compound to be an aldehyde containing ___________ in the parent chain.",
    "answer": "7 carbon atoms",
    "explanation": "Heptanal indicates the compound to be an aldehyde containing 7 carbon atoms in the parent chain. Reference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 346; Paragraph No. 8)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> Nomenclature of organic compounds with functional group",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Substituent at 7th Carbon atom",
    "option_b": "7 carbon atoms",
    "option_c": "7 substituent",
    "option_d": "8 carbon atoms",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 170
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 241505,
    "question": "Identify the compound A and B from the given reaction :\n\nROH+ SOCl₂----> R-Cl + (A) + (B)",
    "answer": "SO₂+HCl",
    "explanation": "The hydroxyl group of an alcohol is replaced by halogen on reaction with concentrated halogen acids, phosphorus halides or thionyl chloride  \n\n(Reference: NCERT Chemistry Class 12; Page 294; Paragraph No.1)\ndiagram(ne2443)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Haloalkanes and Haloarenes >> NCERT Reactions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "POCl₃+HCl",
    "option_b": "PCl₃+H₂0",
    "option_c": "SO₂+HCl",
    "option_d": "HCl only",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 171
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 41501,
    "question": "Which theory introduced quantum mechanical principles?",
    "answer": "Valence bond theory(VBT)",
    "explanation": "Similarly the VSEPR theory gives the geometry of simple molecules but theoretically, it does not explain them and also it has limited applications. \n\nTo overcome these limitations the two important theories based on quantum mechanical principles are introduced. \n\nReference: (NCERT chemistry Class 11; page 117; Paragraph 2)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Chemical bonding and molecular structure >> VB theory",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Valence bond theory(VBT)",
    "option_b": "Lewis Theory",
    "option_c": "VSEPR",
    "option_d": "None of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 172
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 121606,
    "question": "Assertion:  (π) bonds provide the most reactive centres in molecules containing multiple bonds.\n\nReason: The electron charge cloud of the π bond is highly reactive due to its availability to attacking reagents.",
    "answer": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "explanation": "In a pi bond formation, parallel orientation of the two p orbitals on adjacent atoms is necessary for a proper sideways overlap. The electron charge cloud of the pi bond is located above and below the plane of bonding atoms. This distribution of electron charge makes the electrons easily available to attacking reagents, resulting in highly reactive centres in the molecule.Reference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 335; Paragraph No.3)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> Assertion- Reason Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is the correct explanation of the assertion",
    "option_b": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is not the correct explanation of the assertion.",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but reason is false",
    "option_d": "Both Assertion and reason are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 173
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 261027,
    "question": "Soda Lime is the mixture of?",
    "answer": "NaOH and CaO in the ratio of 3 :1",
    "explanation": "Carboxylic acids lose carbon dioxide to form hydrocarbons when their sodium salts are heated with soda lime (NaOH and CaO in the ratio of 3 : 1). \n\nThe reaction is known as decarboxylation.\n\nReference: (NCERT - Class 12 Page-383 Paragraph -2)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Aldehydes,ketones & carboxylic acids >> Chemical Properties",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "NaOH and CaO in the ratio of 3 : 2",
    "option_b": "NaOH and CaO in the ratio of 1: 3",
    "option_c": "NaOH and CaO in the ratio of 3 :1",
    "option_d": "NaOH and CaO in the ratio of 2: 3",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 174
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 41418,
    "question": "AB₃E₂ type of molecules have :",
    "answer": "T- shaped molecular geometry",
    "explanation": "The electronic arrangement in AB₃E₂ is trigonal bipyramidal the presence of 2 lone pairs force it adopt T-shaped so as to minimize the repulsion between bond pairs and lone pairs.\n\nAs shown in diagram \n\nReference: (NCERT chemistry Class 11; page 115; Table 4.7) diagram(ne0411)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Chemical bonding and molecular structure >> VSEPR theory",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "L- shaped molecular geometry",
    "option_b": "T- shaped molecular geometry",
    "option_c": "V- shaped molecular geometry",
    "option_d": "None of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 175
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 240202,
    "question": "What is the basis of classification of monohalogen compounds?",
    "answer": "On basis of hybridization of carbon atom to which halogen is attached",
    "explanation": "Mono Halo Compounds may further be classified according to the hybridisation of the carbon atom to which the halogen is bonded.  \n\n(Reference: NCERT Chemistry Class 12; Page 290; Paragraph No. 2)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Haloalkanes and Haloarenes >> Classification",
    "difficulty_level": 1,
    "option_a": "On basis of number of halogen atom",
    "option_b": "On basis of polarity of compound",
    "option_c": "On basis of physical property",
    "option_d": "On basis of hybridization of carbon atom to which halogen is attached",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 176
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 40929,
    "question": "Choose the correct option regarding the following assertion(A) and reason(R):\n\nA: A qualitative measure of the stability of an ionic compound is provided by its enthalpy of lattice formation and not simply by achieving octet of electrons around the ionic species in gaseous state.\nR: The energy released in the formation of the crystal lattice is more than the energy absorbed",
    "answer": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is not a correct explanation of assertion",
    "explanation": "In ionic solids, the sum of the electron gain enthalpy and the ionization enthalpy may be positive but still the crystal structure gets stabilized due to the energy released in the formation of the crystal lattice. \n\nTherefore, the energy released in the processes is more than the energy absorbed. \n\nThus a qualitative measure of the stability of an ionic compound is provided by its enthalpy of lattice formation and not simply by achieving octet of electrons around the ionic species in gaseous state. \n\nReference: (NCERT chemistry Class 11; page 106; paragraph no.3)",
    "topic_name": "Inorganic Chemistry >> Chemical bonding and molecular structure >> Ionic or electrovalent bond",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "Both assertion and reason are true and reason is a correct explanation of assertion",
    "option_b": "Both assertion and reason are true but reason is not a correct explanation of assertion",
    "option_c": "Assertion is true but the reason is false",
    "option_d": "Both assertion and reason are false",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 177
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 120629,
    "question": "What is the IUPAC name for the compound in the given diagram(1263)",
    "answer": "2-Methylbutanamide",
    "explanation": "Functional group should get the lowest number with longest carbon chain possible hers suffix amide is used and it's carbon is the given the first priority. Reference: (NCERT Chemistry Class 11; Page No. 344; Paragraph No. 2)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Organic chemistry - some basic principles and techniques >> Nomenclature of organic compounds with functional group",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "2-Ethylbutanamide",
    "option_b": "2-Methylbutanamide",
    "option_c": "1-Amino-2-methylpropane",
    "option_d": "None of these",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 178
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 261230,
    "question": "Acetophenone when reacted with a base, C₂H₅ONa, yields a stable compound which has the structure given in diagram(n26090)",
    "answer": "c",
    "explanation": "The first step is a simple condensation reaction. \n\nThe last step is an example of E1 mechanism and the leaving group is hydroxide, which is unusual. \n\nStill this step manages to take place owing to the stability incorporated therein the product, which is a conjugated carbonyl compound.\n\n(NEET:2008)\ndiagram(ne26090)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Aldehydes,ketones & carboxylic acids >> Previous Year Questions",
    "difficulty_level": 3,
    "option_a": "a",
    "option_b": "b",
    "option_c": "c",
    "option_d": "d",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 179
  },
  {
    "unique_id": 131208,
    "question": "Which of them will not be formed on cracking of C6H14?",
    "answer": "C5H10",
    "explanation": "Higher alkanes on heating to higher temperature decompose into lower alkanes, alkenes etc. \n\nSuch a decomposition reaction into smaller fragments by the application of heat is called pyrolysis or cracking.\n\nReference: (NCERT Chemistry Class-11, Page-382, Paragraph - 7) Refer diagram(ne1370)",
    "topic_name": "Organic Chemistry >> Hydrocarbon >> NCERT Reactions",
    "difficulty_level": 2,
    "option_a": "CH4",
    "option_b": "C6H12",
    "option_c": "C5H10",
    "option_d": "C3H6",
    "quiz_type": "mcq",
    "id": 180
  }
]